<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[koyu's personal website]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Discover the projects of a forward-thinking developer passionate about ethical technology, operating systems, audio processing, and privacy-focused software. Explore cutting-edge innovations in voice technology and open-source development.]]></description>
        <link>https://leonie.lgbt</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 12:55:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://leonie.lgbt/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From X260 to the Stars: How Linux Is Quietly Taking Over]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I&#x27;m lounging here with my trusty ThinkPad X260, running Sway as my window manager and Kanshi seamlessly managing my display profiles. Everything operates smoothly, no bloatware, no intrusive telemetry, no unnecessary clutter. It&#x27;s just me and my system, tailored to perfection. The hum of the fans is barely noticeable, the keyboard worn smooth from years of dedicated service. This machine, simple and sturdy, is more than enough for everything I need, and that&#x27;s the magic.</p><p>And now? The world is catching on.</p><p>PewDiePie, one of the most popular YouTubers, recently made headlines by switching to Linux. In his video titled <a href="https://youtu.be/pVI_smLgTY0?si=0LJctUqavY5SY9Zi">&quot;I installed Linux (so should you)&quot;</a>, he documents his journey from Windows to Linux Mint and eventually to Arch Linux. Instead of struggling, Pewds handled his Arch setup with surprising skill, setting up Hyprland as his window manager and even writing his own scripts and dotfiles. Watching him confidently tweak his system was almost cathartic; it&#x27;s proof that even the biggest names can thrive when freedom is on the table. His honest excitement, the customizations, the new workflows, the empowerment, mirrors what so many Linux users experience when they realize they are no longer trapped by corporate design.</p><p>Similarly, James Lee, a renowned animator, has transitioned to Linux, citing the freedom and efficiency it provides for his creative work. In discussions on platforms like Reddit, users highlight his move as a significant endorsement of Linux&#x27;s capabilities for professionals in creative fields. (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/linux_gaming/comments/1htm70e/popular_animator_james_lee_switches_to_linux/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Source</a>) His switch reflects a growing sentiment among artists and developers who are fed up with closed ecosystems and subscription traps. It&#x27;s not just a tech thing anymore; it&#x27;s a lifestyle choice, a rejection of unnecessary complexity and corporate gatekeeping.</p><p>While others grapple with system bloat and restrictive ecosystems, we navigate our self-built systems with ease. It&#x27;s not about being edgy or &quot;tech elite.&quot; It&#x27;s about reclaiming ownership. Your data, your system, your rules. It&#x27;s about understanding that technology should serve you, not the other way around. This isn&#x27;t just a trend; it&#x27;s a cultural shift. One built on autonomy, transparency, and genuine craftsmanship. One built on the simple idea that creativity thrives best where control and freedom are given back to the user.</p><p>Linux isn&#x27;t taking over in a loud, headline-grabbing explosion. It&#x27;s seeping in quietly, reshaping how people think about technology. It&#x27;s in the indie game developers ditching proprietary engines. It&#x27;s in the digital artists breaking free from expensive subscription models. It&#x27;s in the students, the researchers, the musicians, all building, sharing, collaborating without artificial barriers.</p><p>Meanwhile, Windows, the system literally named after &quot;windows,&quot; continues to offer some of the worst window management imaginable. Windows users find themselves constantly dragging, resizing, rearranging, and fighting their workflow, trapped in an outdated paradigm that feels increasingly clumsy compared to the elegant, dynamic tiling of Sway, Hyprland, and other modern Linux environments. It&#x27;s ironic: the platform that made &quot;windows&quot; its core metaphor still doesn&#x27;t know how to handle them properly.</p><p></p><p>And me? I&#x27;m still here, lounging with my Sway setup, Kanshi managing my displays, a satisfied grin, and a front-row seat to the future. Watching as the seeds we&#x27;ve planted for years finally break through the concrete.</p><p>Because make no mistake: the future is open. And it&#x27;s already here.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/from-x260-to-the-stars-how-linux-is-quietly-taking-over.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/from-x260-to-the-stars-how-linux-is-quietly-taking-over.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 08:20:26 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Signal, Trump, Elon, and the "Leak": Why Signal is Still Secure]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h2>The Incident: A Journalist&#x27;s Unexpected Invitation</h2><p>In March 2025, Jeffrey Goldberg, editor-in-chief of <em>The Atlantic</em>, was inadvertently added to a Signal group chat where top U.S. officials were discussing sensitive military operations in Yemen. This group included notable figures such as Vice President J.D. Vance and Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth. Goldberg, initially skeptical about the authenticity of the invitation, found himself privy to confidential deliberations, which he later reported on, igniting a media frenzy. (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/mar/26/new-revelations-us-signal-leak-claims-doubt-yemen?utm_source=chatgpt.com">The Guardian</a>)</p><p></p><h2>Trump and Musk Weigh In</h2><p>In response to the breach, former President Donald Trump suggested that Signal &quot;could be defective,&quot; implying that the app&#x27;s security might be compromised. (<a href="https://nypost.com/2025/03/26/us-news/trump-says-signal-could-be-defective/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">New York Post</a>)</p><p>Elon Musk also entered the conversation, alleging that Signal had &quot;known vulnerabilities.&quot; These statements cast doubts on the app&#x27;s reliability, leading to widespread speculation.</p><p></p><h2>Signal&#x27;s Robust Defense</h2><p>Contrary to these claims, Signal&#x27;s leadership and cybersecurity experts have consistently defended the app&#x27;s integrity. Meredith Whittaker, President of the Signal Foundation, emphasized that Signal maintains full end-to-end encryption and prioritizes user privacy. She highlighted that while other platforms might collect metadata, Signal&#x27;s open-source, nonprofit model ensures strict application of encryption to protect user data. (<a href="https://www.geo.tv/latest/597147-signal-ceo-defends-app-security-following-us-military-leak?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Geo.tv</a>)</p><p>Furthermore, the incident involving Goldberg was attributed to human error rather than a flaw in Signal&#x27;s technology. Accidentally adding an unintended participant to a group chat is a user mistake, not an indication of a security breach within the app itself. (<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signalgate-isnt-about-signal?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Wired</a>)</p><p></p><h2>Why Signal Remains a Secure Choice</h2><p>Despite the high-profile mishap, Signal continues to be a leading choice for secure communication. Here&#x27;s why:</p><ul><li><strong>End-to-End Encryption:</strong> Signal encrypts messages on the sender&#x27;s device and decrypts them only on the recipient&#x27;s device, ensuring that no intermediaries, including Signal itself, can access the content.</li><li><strong>Minimal Data Collection:</strong> Unlike other messaging platforms, Signal collects virtually no user data, safeguarding your personal information from potential exploitation.</li><li><strong>Open-Source Transparency:</strong> Signal&#x27;s code is open-source, allowing security experts worldwide to inspect and verify its integrity, fostering trust through transparency.</li></ul><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>The recent controversy underscores a fundamental truth: even the most secure technologies cannot compensate for human error. While the accidental inclusion of a journalist in a sensitive group chat was a significant oversight, it does not reflect a deficiency in Signal&#x27;s security protocols. Users must exercise caution and double-check participant lists when handling confidential information. In the realm of private communication, Signal remains a robust and reliable tool, provided it is used responsibly.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/signal-trump-elon-and-the-leak-why-signal-is-still-secure.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/signal-trump-elon-and-the-leak-why-signal-is-still-secure.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 07:49:22 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[freiOS: A New Way to Experience Computing]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been hunting for a fresh, secure, and lightweight operating system, then freiOS might just be the breath of fresh air you need. Built with simplicity, speed, and security in mind, freiOS isn’t just another OS — it’s a platform designed for users who value efficiency, sustainability, and privacy.</p><h3>A Modern Approach to OS Design</h3><p>What really sets freiOS apart is its focus on performance without compromising security. When you boot it up, you’re not only greeted with a sleek interface but also a fast, responsive environment that works seamlessly on both modern and older hardware. You won’t find bloated features slowing you down here; instead, it’s all about doing more with less. Whether you’re managing daily tasks, running productivity apps, or just browsing the web, freiOS ensures your computer stays fast and secure, even under load.</p><h3>Built-In Security</h3><p>In today’s digital world, data privacy is more important than ever, and freiOS takes that seriously. The OS incorporates strong encryption protocols and built-in privacy features to ensure your data stays safe, no matter what you’re doing. freiOS is a trustworthy option for users who want to maintain control over their personal information. Whether you’re using it for personal tasks or business work, you can rely on its built-in features to keep your data secure.</p><h3>Efficiency Meets Simplicity</h3><p>One of the standout features of freiOS is its intuitive, minimalist GNOME desktop environment. There’s no overwhelming clutter, just a straightforward workspace where everything is where it needs to be. This user-centric design is perfect for those who value a clean, distraction-free computing experience. Whether you’re working from home or on the go, freiOS provides the right tools to get the job done quickly and efficiently.</p><p>And with full localization options, it’s easy to adapt to your own preferences and language. The system supports a wide range of regional settings, such as date formats and currency symbols, ensuring a smooth experience regardless of your location.</p><h3>Out-of-the-Box Essentials</h3><p>FreiOS doesn’t leave you hanging when it comes to apps. It comes preloaded with the essential tools you need to get started. LibreOffice, for word processing and spreadsheets, Evolution for managing email and calendar, and more. You won’t have to scramble around downloading software just to get productive. Plus, the OS integrates seamlessly with services that most users rely on for their daily tasks, making it a great choice right from the start.</p><h3>Hardware Compatibility and Longevity</h3><p>Not only does it offer performance, but freiOS is also designed to be hardware-friendly. Whether you’re using an old laptop or a modern desktop, it supports a wide range of components, including graphics cards from Nvidia, AMD, and Intel. The system also provides pre-configured ISO files that make installation a breeze — no headache, just an easy setup that works from the get-go.</p><p>By optimizing the OS for both modern and older hardware, freiOS is contributing to the reduction of electronic waste — a huge benefit in today’s environmentally conscious world. Its lightweight design allows older systems to run smoothly, helping them stay relevant longer and saving them from obsolescence.</p><h3>A Perfect Fit for Local Needs</h3><p>What makes freiOS even more compelling is how it’s subtly optimized for local needs. While it’s designed to be a globally accessible operating system, freiOS takes into account the specifics of the German market. It integrates regional settings like language, date formats, and even currency symbols to provide a more seamless and familiar experience for German users. These thoughtful details ensure that the system feels intuitive and efficient for those based in Germany, further enhancing its usability and appeal.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>If you’re looking for an operating system that values speed, security, and sustainability, freiOS should definitely be on your radar. With its user-friendly interface, solid security, seamless hardware compatibility, and thoughtful design, it’s a great choice for anyone from casual users to those who want to push the boundaries of their machines. The future of computing is clean, efficient, and secure, and freiOS is paving the way.</p><p>Whether you’re tired of bloated, slow systems or just want something more minimalist and dependable, freiOS gives you everything you need to get the job done. Give it a try and experience computing in a whole new way.</p><div style="display:none">Unknown block type "card", specify a component for it in the `components.types` option</div>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/freios-a-new-way-to-experience-computing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/freios-a-new-way-to-experience-computing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 08:18:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[koyu.space was still here all the time – now as a PDS!]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>koyu.space has been quietly present for a while, but it’s been a little less vocal about its existence lately. That’s changing now. koyu.space has evolved into a Personal Data Server (PDS), making it part of the decentralized social web.</p><h2>What does that mean?</h2><p>koyu.space now operates on the <a href="https://atproto.com/">Authenticated Transfer Protocol (AT Protocol)</a>, the same protocol that powers <a href="https://bsky.app/">Bluesky</a>. Unlike traditional social media platforms, where all your data is locked into a single company’s walled garden, a PDS lets you have more control over your information. You’re not just the product – you’re the one holding the keys to your own data.</p><p>If you were part of koyu.space before, or you’re curious about what’s different now, I’m opening up invites for the next chapter of this journey! If you’d like to join, just reach out to me, and I’ll send you an invite.</p><h2>Bluesky vs. Mastodon</h2><p>While we’re on the topic of decentralized platforms, let’s talk a bit about how Bluesky compares to Mastodon – two popular alternatives to traditional social media.</p><p>Both are part of the Fediverse, but Bluesky runs on the AT Protocol, while Mastodon uses ActivityPub. The AT Protocol offers some key advantages:</p><ol><li><strong>Improved Scalability and Performance</strong>: Bluesky’s protocol is designed with scalability in mind. It handles large volumes of traffic and user data with greater efficiency, making it a smoother experience for users. Mastodon, on the other hand, can sometimes struggle with performance due to its decentralized nature, especially on smaller instances.</li><li><strong>Better Data Control</strong>: The AT Protocol gives users more control over their data. It allows for features like private profiles, content moderation at the individual level, and greater customization. Mastodon does offer some of these features, but Bluesky’s implementation is more streamlined and accessible.</li><li><strong>Ease of Use</strong>: Bluesky’s user interface is sleek and designed with simplicity in mind. It’s easy to navigate, and you don’t have to worry about joining a specific instance or server to participate. Mastodon can be more complicated for newcomers because it requires joining specific instances that have different rules, policies, and content moderation standards.</li><li><strong>Cross-Platform Compatibility</strong>: Bluesky, due to its protocol design, is built to be more compatible with other platforms and social networks in the future. It provides a strong foundation for expanding the decentralized web. Mastodon has made incredible progress, but its ecosystem still feels somewhat segmented.</li><li><strong>Storage Efficiency</strong>: One of the standout advantages of Bluesky is that it doesn’t fill up your storage the way Mastodon can. Mastodon’s backend is notoriously inefficient, and my previous instance on Mastodon collected over <strong>3TB</strong> of data before it was shut down. This massive amount of data just from running an instance made it increasingly difficult to maintain and scale. Bluesky’s more efficient infrastructure ensures that data doesn’t accumulate unnecessarily, making it far easier to manage.</li></ol><p>That said, both Bluesky and Mastodon are excellent options for those looking to move away from centralized social media. It all comes down to what you value more: performance and scalability, or community-driven moderation and openness.</p><p>If you’re ready to explore a more decentralized way of socializing, join koyu.space and start engaging with a new kind of platform.</p><p>See you there! 🚀</p><div style="display:none">Unknown block type "blockref", specify a component for it in the `components.types` option</div>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/koyu-space-was-still-here-all-the-time-now-as-a-pds.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/koyu-space-was-still-here-all-the-time-now-as-a-pds.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Back in the Ink: A Fresh Start with Splatoon 3]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>For a while, my Switch Lite sat forgotten, gathering dust in the corner. I had moved on to other things, including The Finals, my competitive shooter of choice on Linux. But a recent disaster—when The Finals completely broke after a frustrating update—finally pushed me to dust off my old console. The game wouldn’t even launch anymore, and after countless tweaks to make it work on Linux, I was done. I needed something fresh, and that’s when I found Splatoon 3.</p><p></p><p>I’ve never been part of the Splatoon craze. I missed the hype around the first two games, never owned a Wii U, and didn’t get into the series until the third installment. But once I fired up Splatoon 3, I was hooked immediately. This game is something else.</p><p></p><p>The vibe of Splatoon 3? Electric. The city is vibrant and full of life, and the music is a hyperactive blend of squid-pop that matches the action on screen. But beyond the charming aesthetic, the core gameplay is what keeps me coming back. It’s a turf war where your weapon of choice is ink, and the goal is to cover as much ground as possible while splatting opponents. It’s addicting. The strategy involved in choosing your weapons, balancing your loadout, and coordinating with teammates makes it feel less like a simple shooter and more like a competitive dance with ink and paint.</p><p></p><p>And now, with the official announcement of the Switch 2, I’m even more excited. Sure, there have been rumors and leaks for months, but the real deal is finally here. As we inch closer to its release, I can’t help but imagine how Splatoon 3’s ink-splattering chaos will look on a beefier console with better graphics and smoother framerates. But despite the hype for the new hardware, there’s something oddly satisfying about revisiting a system that’s past its prime. It’s like rereading a favorite book before you dive into a new series—familiar but still thrilling.</p><p></p><p>For now, though, I’m content to stay in the world of Splatoon 3. It’s the right game at the right time. I’m having a blast dodging rollers, launching Tenta Missiles, and trying to keep up with the player who’s always just a little bit too good. The ink might dry eventually, but right now, I’m just soaking in every colorful, chaotic moment.</p><p></p><p>As for The Finals, I’ll be back once the game recovers from its latest break. Version 5.6 has completely broken the game on Linux, and until that gets patched, I’m staying in Splatoon 3’s world of ink-splattered mayhem. Here’s to new memories, one splash at a time.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/back-in-the-ink-a-fresh-start-with-splatoon-3.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/back-in-the-ink-a-fresh-start-with-splatoon-3.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 08:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SteamOS Beta: A Turning Point for Linux Gaming]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been following Valve’s efforts to push Linux gaming forward, and the upcoming beta release of SteamOS for third-party handheld devices feels like a significant step. As a Linux enthusiast and gamer, it’s been fascinating to watch how far things have come—and how much more potential there is.</p><p></p><h3>SteamOS Beta for Handheld Devices</h3><p></p><p>Valve is about to release a beta version of SteamOS for devices beyond the Steam Deck. That means more handheld PCs will be able to run SteamOS. The Lenovo Legion Go S, launching in May 2025, will be one of the first to take advantage of this. It’s interesting to see how this device, with its 8-inch VRR screen, AMD Ryzen processor, and $499.99 starting price, will contribute to making portable Linux gaming more mainstream. Having a company like Lenovo onboard suggests growing confidence in SteamOS as a platform.</p><p></p><h3>Why This Matters for Linux Gaming</h3><p></p><p>Valve’s contributions to Linux gaming have been transformative:</p><p></p><ul><li><strong>Proton</strong>: Since its release in 2018, Proton has significantly expanded the number of Windows games that run on Linux, making gaming on Linux far more accessible.</li></ul><p></p><ul><li><strong>Third-Party Support</strong>: SteamOS support for devices like the Asus ROG Ally shows Valve’s commitment to building a more open gaming ecosystem.</li></ul><p></p><ul><li><strong>Arch Linux Development</strong>: By investing in Arch Linux, the foundation for SteamOS, Valve improves performance and stability across the entire Linux gaming scene.</li></ul><p></p><h3>Why This Matters to Me</h3><p></p><p>This isn’t just about new hardware or software—it’s about freedom of choice. More platforms running Linux means more options for gamers and developers alike. I’m hoping to see more native Linux support as SteamOS grows, making Linux an even stronger alternative to proprietary systems.</p><p></p><p>The SteamOS beta and devices like the Legion Go S could mark a turning point. I’m looking forward to seeing where this goes—and to playing more games on an open platform.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/steamos-beta-a-turning-point-for-linux-gaming.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/steamos-beta-a-turning-point-for-linux-gaming.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 18:18:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vinyl is great again]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend at the flea market, I found an old man selling his second record player. He just wanted to get rid of it, and for 10€, I couldn’t resist. It’s been a solid decision ever since.</p><p></p><h2>Vinyl: A Ritual in an Age of Convenience</h2><p></p><p>Vinyl is more than just a way to play music; it’s a ritual. From picking out an album to carefully placing the needle on the record, it forces you to slow down and be present. There’s something satisfying about sliding a record out of its sleeve, setting it on the turntable, and lowering the needle. It’s a tactile process that digital music doesn’t offer.</p><p></p><p>The crackle that happens when the needle hits the groove? It’s like the soundtrack to your anticipation. It’s not perfect, but that’s part of its charm. Each little imperfection feels personal, making the experience feel more human. The sound feels alive in a way that streaming can’t replicate.</p><p></p><h2>Why Vinyl Still Matters</h2><p></p><p>These days, we have music on-demand everywhere—Spotify, our phones, even through voice assistants. It’s quick, easy, and always available. I love using Spotify to discover new artists and my iPod is perfect for listening to my most-played tracks. But vinyl brings something different to the table.</p><p></p><p>With vinyl, you can’t skip ahead or hit shuffle. You put on an album, start it at the beginning, and listen all the way through. It forces you to pay attention in a way digital music doesn’t. You notice details—things you might overlook when you’re constantly swiping through playlists. Vinyl asks for your attention, and in return, it gives you something a little more rewarding.</p><p></p><h2>A Link to the Past</h2><p></p><p>There’s something about vinyl that connects you to the past. It’s not just about the music; it’s about the physical experience. The slight wear on the album cover, the grooves in the record that catch the light—all of these things add character and tell a story. When you play a record, you’re not just hearing a song—you’re tapping into a shared history, an experience that’s been passed down through generations.</p><p></p><p>The record player I bought wasn’t just an object; it had a story too. The man who sold it to me had probably used it for years, playing countless albums. Now it’s here with me, continuing its journey with new records and new memories.</p><p></p><h2>Why Vinyl Feels So Right</h2><p></p><p>In a world where everything moves fast and we can get any song we want instantly, vinyl feels like a reminder to slow down. It’s about taking the time to fully experience something, rather than rushing through it. Vinyl isn’t perfect, but maybe that’s why it feels so right—it’s real.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/vinyl-is-great-again.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/vinyl-is-great-again.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 18:19:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Linux, Especially Xubuntu, Shines on Weak Laptops]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever owned a lightweight, low-powered laptop—something akin to a Chromebook—you know how quickly it can falter under the weight of traditional operating systems. Windows can feel sluggish, and ChromeOS, while fast, locks you into a single ecosystem. Enter Linux: a flexible and efficient solution that can transform your underpowered machine into a surprisingly capable device.</p><p></p><p>Among the many Linux distributions, <strong>Xubuntu</strong> stands out as an excellent choice for weak laptops. Here’s why:</p><p></p><h3>Why Linux is Perfect for Weak Laptops</h3><p></p><ol><li><strong>Resource Efficiency</strong><br/>Linux can operate with minimal hardware requirements. Weak laptops benefit immensely from the ability to run a full-fledged OS without choking on background tasks or unnecessary features.</li><li><strong>Customizability Without Sacrifice</strong><br/>Linux lets you fine-tune your system to prioritize what you need, avoiding unnecessary bloat. With distributions like Xubuntu, the balance between simplicity and functionality is just right.</li><li><strong>Free and Open Source</strong><br/>Say goodbye to expensive licenses and forced upgrades. Linux is free to use and doesn’t require you to buy into an ecosystem.</li><li><strong>Secure and Reliable</strong><br/>Linux distributions are known for their security and stability, even on weaker hardware. Xubuntu, built on Ubuntu’s solid foundation, inherits these strengths.</li></ol><p></p><h3>Why Xubuntu Stands Out</h3><p></p><p>Xubuntu is built around <strong>Xfce</strong>, a desktop environment that’s fast, lightweight, and user-friendly. It strikes a perfect balance for low-powered devices, offering:</p><p></p><ol><li><strong>A Lightweight Desktop Environment</strong><br/>Xfce is designed for performance. It’s light on memory and CPU usage, allowing even underwhelming hardware to feel snappy.</li><li><strong>Ease of Use</strong><br/>Xubuntu’s clean, intuitive interface ensures that you don’t need to be a Linux expert to get started. It’s welcoming to beginners and functional enough for seasoned users.</li><li><strong>Ubuntu Ecosystem</strong><br/>With Xubuntu, you get access to Ubuntu’s extensive software library and community support, making it easy to find solutions or applications tailored to your needs.</li><li><strong>Low Resource Usage</strong><br/>Xubuntu ships with lightweight default applications like the Thunar file manager and Mousepad text editor, which keep your system fast while providing essential functionality.</li></ol><p></p><p><strong>Revive, Don’t Replac</strong>e</p><p></p><p>Linux, and specifically Xubuntu, empowers you to make the most of your weak laptop. Whether you’re looking to save money, reduce e-waste, or enjoy the freedom of open-source software, Xubuntu provides a snappy, reliable, and user-friendly experience that far exceeds expectations for low-powered machines.</p><p></p><p>So, before you give up on your aging or low-powered laptop, give Linux a shot. Xubuntu might just surprise you with how far it can take you.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-linux-especially-xubuntu-shines-on-weak-laptops.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-linux-especially-xubuntu-shines-on-weak-laptops.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 18:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Just Use Linux]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’re like me and have been keeping an eye on the tech world, you’ve probably heard about Microsoft’s latest move—the <em>Recall</em> feature. This feature is now mandatory, and if you don’t opt into it, your Explorer will break. Yes, you read that right: Your file manager, the core of your daily OS interaction, can just decide to stop functioning unless you bow to the latest demand from Microsoft. Sound ridiculous? It is. And it’s just one more reason why I’m telling you—just use Linux.</p><p></p><p>Let me explain.</p><p></p><h3>1. <strong>Freedom and Control</strong></h3><p></p><p>When you run Linux, you’re in charge. You decide what gets installed, when updates happen, and how your system operates. With Windows, it feels more and more like you’re just renting your OS, rather than owning it. Features like <em>Recall</em> are a prime example. Why should your system force an update or feature on you, especially when it can break core functionality if you don’t comply?</p><p></p><p>Linux flips that on its head. It’s open-source, meaning anyone can contribute to and audit the code. You’re not at the mercy of some corporation’s boardroom decisions. Your operating system isn’t a black box. You can configure it however you like—tweak every detail if that’s your thing, or keep it as simple as possible.</p><p></p><h3>2. <strong>No Forced Features Like Recall</strong></h3><p></p><p>The fact that Microsoft is tying system stability to a mandatory feature like <em>Recall</em> should set off alarm bells. What will be next? If you don’t opt into telemetry sharing, will your search function break? Or will updates be forced on you at inconvenient times, even if they wreck compatibility with critical software? (Oh wait, that’s already happening too.)</p><p></p><p>On Linux, features are opt-in. You choose which updates to apply, and you’re never forced into a corner where your system breaks if you don’t follow arbitrary rules. The community-driven development means changes are discussed openly, reviewed thoroughly, and distributed through trusted channels.</p><p></p><h3>3. <strong>Privacy</strong></h3><p></p><p>Windows has long had issues with privacy, whether it’s tracking user activity, collecting data for telemetry, or locking down proprietary software that prevents transparency. Features like <em>Recall</em> are just another example of how you’re giving up more control and privacy with each passing year.</p><p></p><p>On Linux, privacy is foundational. You have full transparency and control over what your system is doing. Want to know if your OS is phoning home to its creators? You can inspect the code and networking yourself. There’s no hidden data collection, no forced opt-ins. You can stay off the grid if that’s what you want, all while using a fully functional OS.</p><p></p><h3>4. <strong>Stability and Performance</strong></h3><p></p><p>The biggest fear for most people switching from Windows to Linux is stability and software support. But Linux has come a long way, and many distros are now extremely stable—if not more stable than Windows. With Windows, you constantly deal with patches that seem to fix one thing and break three others. Mandatory updates at inconvenient times. Features like <em>Recall</em> causing unnecessary disruptions.</p><p></p><p>On Linux, updates are more predictable and stable. You don’t wake up one day to find your file explorer has stopped working because of a bad decision on Microsoft’s end. And as for performance? Linux is often lighter and faster than Windows, especially if you’re using a desktop environment like XFCE or a window manager like i3. It’s an OS that runs efficiently on both older hardware and modern rigs, letting you use your system’s resources for what matters—not the OS itself.</p><p></p><h3>5. <strong>Open-Source Ecosystem</strong></h3><p></p><p>One of the joys of Linux is the vast array of open-source software available. You aren’t stuck using clunky proprietary alternatives. Most tools, whether for development, design, media creation, or productivity, are free and open. Plus, they’re constantly improving thanks to a global community of passionate contributors.</p><p></p><p>If you need specialized software, chances are Linux has an equivalent—or something better. And if you’re a power user or developer, the Linux environment gives you unparalleled flexibility with scripting, automation, and customization.</p><p></p><h3>6. <strong>No More Bloatware</strong></h3><p></p><p>Remember when you first boot up a Windows PC? All the pre-installed junk, ads in your start menu, the useless games and trials that you didn’t ask for. That’s bloatware. And it’s a hassle to remove it all. The <em>Recall</em> fiasco is just an extension of that bloat—it’s something you didn’t ask for, yet can break your system if you don’t comply.</p><p></p><p>On Linux, there’s no bloatware. You install only what you want, and that’s it. If you choose a minimal distribution like Arch Linux or Debian, your system stays lean and focused on your needs.</p><p></p><h3>7. <strong>Community Support</strong></h3><p></p><p>With Linux, you’re not alone. There’s a massive community of users and developers who are constantly sharing knowledge, solving problems, and improving the ecosystem. You don’t have to wait for an official support team to get back to you in a few business days. Forums, IRC channels, Reddit threads, and countless blogs are filled with helpful people eager to guide you through any issue.</p><p></p><h3>8. <strong>It’s Time to Break Free</strong></h3><p></p><p>Microsoft’s decision to force <em>Recall</em> on users is just the latest in a long line of moves that make Windows feel more like a walled garden than ever before. It’s time to break free from these corporate-driven restrictions and regain control of your own computing experience.</p><p></p><p>Linux offers you freedom, privacy, stability, and the joy of working with an open system built by people for people—not by corporations for profit. Whether you’re a power user, a developer, or just someone who’s tired of feeling like you’re losing control of your own machine, Linux is ready for you.</p><p></p><p>It’s not just an alternative to Windows; it’s a better way to compute. So, stop putting up with mandatory features, data collection, and arbitrary restrictions. Just use Linux. You won’t regret it.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/just-use-linux.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/just-use-linux.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 17:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unveiling Project Next: Anya]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>When you’re building a gaming PC that combines performance, efficiency, and longevity, you need to be deliberate with each component. In my recent build, I’ve focused not only on performance but also on ensuring the rig is <em>passively cooled</em> – an often overlooked approach that keeps things silent without sacrificing functionality.<br/>Let’s dive into the hardware and explore how it all comes together in a fanless system that’s built to last.</p><h3><strong>1. AMD Ryzen 5 7600X: The Heart of the System</strong></h3><p>With <strong>6 cores and 12 threads</strong>, the <strong>AMD Ryzen 5 7600X</strong> running at <strong>4.70 GHz</strong> is a mid-range powerhouse. Whether I’m gaming, working on productivity tasks, or even handling light workstation duties, this CPU excels thanks to its excellent single-core performance and respectable multi-threading capabilities. The decision to go with the Ryzen 5 7600X wasn’t just about performance, though—its efficient Zen 4 architecture ensures it runs cool, making it perfect for a passively cooled system.<br/>In a fanless setup, temperature management becomes even more critical, and the 7600X’s balance between speed and thermal efficiency makes it an ideal choice for my needs.</p><h3><strong>2. Alphacool Core Ocean T38 AIO 360mm: Efficient Passive Cooling</strong></h3><p>While most gaming PCs rely on traditional fans, I’ve opted for a <strong>360mm Alphacool Core Ocean T38 AIO</strong> to handle the cooling. The beauty of this setup is that the large radiator surface area efficiently dissipates heat, even without active airflow. Paired with the low TDP of the Ryzen 5 7600X, this AIO provides enough cooling to keep temperatures under control during intense gaming or high-performance workloads.<br/>Choosing a passive approach means no noise, less dust buildup, and a sleeker overall design. It also requires careful planning when it comes to component placement and heat distribution, but the result is a rig that runs cool and quiet.</p><h3><strong>3. MSI Pro A2620M-E Motherboard: The Foundation</strong></h3><p>The <strong>MSI Pro A2620M-E</strong> motherboard offers everything I need for this build: reliable performance, PCIe 4.0 support, and great compatibility with the rest of the hardware. It’s a no-nonsense choice that ensures stable performance, ample connectivity, and enough headroom for future upgrades.</p><h3><strong>4. 1TB Kingston NV2 NVMe M.2: Fast Storage for Years</strong></h3><p>Storage is critical in any build, and I went for the <strong>1TB Kingston NV2 NVMe M.2 SSD</strong> to ensure I get the fastest speeds with minimal power consumption. Its <strong>PCIe 4.0 interface</strong> and <strong>3D NAND technology</strong> provide ultra-fast read and write speeds, ideal for loading games, large files, or multitasking-heavy workflows.<br/>Not only does it minimize power usage, but its compact M.2 form factor also means no additional airflow is required for cooling—perfect for this fanless build.</p><h3><strong>5. be quiet! Pure Power 11 700W: Silent and Efficient Power Supply</strong></h3><p>For power, I’m using the <strong>700W be quiet! Pure Power 11</strong>, which fits perfectly with the silent theme of this rig. It’s <strong>non-modular</strong>, but the <strong>80+ Gold efficiency</strong> ensures minimal heat generation and power waste, a must when running a passively cooled system. Plus, be quiet! is known for its reliability and silent operation, which is crucial when building a system with no fans.</p><h3><strong>6. NVIDIA GTX 1660 SUPER: Good Performance Without Excessive Heat</strong></h3><p>The <strong>NVIDIA GTX 1660 SUPER</strong> is an excellent match for my needs. While it’s not the latest and greatest, it delivers more than enough power for modern gaming at 1080p75fps. The card also runs relatively cool, which is a big win in a passively cooled setup. This is also only the noisy part of my rig while the rest remains whisper-quiet.</p><h3><strong>7. Lian Li DAN A3-mATX: Compact Case, Sleek Design</strong></h3><p>The <strong>Lian Li DAN A3-mATX</strong> is the ideal case for this build. It’s compact, minimalist and stylish. The case’s design allows for passive cooling to work effectively, as it is optimized for airflow even without traditional fans. A minor hiccup was needing a USB2 header adapter to get the USB-C front port up and running.</p><h3><strong>8. Crucial Pro DDR5 RAM: Fast and Future-Proof</strong></h3><p>Finally, the <strong>32GB Crucial Pro DDR5 RAM</strong> (running at <strong>5600MHz</strong> in Dual-Channel) ensures that my rig won’t bottleneck during intensive gaming or multitasking. DDR5 is the future, and at <strong>32GB</strong>, I have plenty of headroom for the coming years. Its low power consumption also makes it a great match for a passively cooled system, reducing heat output and ensuring efficient performance.</p><h3><strong>Conclusion: The Future of Silent Performance</strong></h3><p>This build is all about creating a balance—powerful enough for today’s gaming and work needs while remaining quiet, efficient, and cool enough to function without traditional fans. With careful component selection, such as the Ryzen 5 7600X and the Alphacool AIO, this rig is a testament to what’s possible when you push the boundaries of what’s expected in PC cooling.<br/>By eliminating fans, I’ve created a system that’s not only silent but efficient and future-proof—ready for years of gaming and productivity without compromising on performance.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/unveiling-project-next-anya.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/unveiling-project-next-anya.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 17:22:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifesto of the IndieWeb: Reclaiming the Web from Convenience and Corporate Control]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1><strong>1. Introduction: The Convenience Trap</strong></h1><p></p><p>The web was born as a decentralized network, an open and free space where individuals could express themselves, communicate, and share ideas without needing the permission or oversight of a central authority. In its early days, it represented a digital commons—a place where anyone could build a website, craft content, and participate in the global conversation.</p><p></p><p>Today, however, the web looks very different. The landscape has been enclosed by corporate platforms that control vast ecosystems and dominate user experiences. The internet has become centralized, fragmented into a handful of massive social networks, media platforms, and services where users no longer own or control their data, content, or even identities. People have been funneled into closed systems that prioritize convenience over freedom, commoditizing their attention and personal information in the process.</p><p></p><p>But the real problem lies not just with these corporations; it’s with us, the users, who have willingly traded freedom for convenience. We’ve clicked “accept” on terms we haven’t read. We’ve created Instagram accounts instead of personal websites. We’ve exchanged our autonomy for the ease of ready-made, pre-packaged services that lock us into their ecosystems. This manifesto calls for a deep, systemic change—a movement away from the traps of convenience and centralized control toward an internet that is once again owned and controlled by individuals.</p><p></p><h3><strong>2. The Problem: Convenience, Corporations, and Centralization</strong></h3><p></p><p>It’s easy to place all the blame on the giant corporations that dominate the web—Facebook (Meta), Google, Amazon, and their counterparts—but the real cancer of the modern internet goes deeper than just the presence of a few big websites. The problem is structural: entire toolkits, ecosystems, and digital infrastructures are built around these corporations, making it virtually impossible for indie projects and alternatives to compete. These companies don’t just own platforms; they own the frameworks, the tools, the standards, and even the browsers that determine how the web operates.</p><p></p><p>Consider Chromium, the engine behind Google Chrome, which is now the foundation for the vast majority of web browsers, giving Google control not only over its browser but over much of the web experience itself. Or take Facebook, which doesn’t just dominate social media but has created an entire ecosystem of services, APIs, and development tools that lock developers and users alike into its orbit. The convenience of these platforms is seductive, and many users, developers, and companies choose the path of least resistance—plugging into these pre-built ecosystems rather than building their own.</p><p></p><p>But we must recognize the consequences of this. We are trading autonomy for ease. We are feeding a system that is designed to commodify our attention, our data, and our creativity. We are giving up the web.</p><p></p><h3><strong>3. The IndieWeb Solution: A Return to Autonomy</strong></h3><p></p><p>The IndieWeb movement represents a radical return to the web’s original promise—a decentralized, user-owned, and user-controlled internet. At its core, the IndieWeb is about <em>empowerment</em>—about giving individuals the tools, knowledge, and frameworks to build their own spaces on the web without relying on corporate intermediaries. It’s about reclaiming the autonomy that we’ve lost in the age of platforms.</p><p></p><p>Key to this movement is the idea that every individual should own their data, their content, and their identity online. This isn’t just a matter of control over personal information (though that’s important too); it’s about reclaiming creative and expressive freedom. It’s about making sure that the web doesn’t belong to a few corporations but to the billions of individuals who use it every day.</p><p></p><p>The IndieWeb isn’t just a call for decentralization; it’s a call to action for users and developers to take back the tools of creation, to reject the pre-built ecosystems of big tech, and to build something new—something truly independent.</p><p></p><h3><strong>4. The Barriers: Why People Choose Convenience</strong></h3><p></p><p>However, if the IndieWeb is to succeed, we must confront a difficult truth: most people won’t willingly leave the convenient platforms they’ve grown accustomed to. Platforms like Facebook, Instagram, YouTube, and TikTok are popular not just because of their corporate backing, but because they are easy. They work out-of-the-box. They offer seamless integration across devices, simple user interfaces, and massive built-in audiences. For the average user, convenience trumps everything else.</p><p></p><p>This convenience, though, is the web’s ultimate enemy. It’s why people accept endless surveillance, manipulation, and control in exchange for a service that simply works. But the IndieWeb’s goal is not to force users to reject convenience; rather, it is to build systems that can compete with the user experience of big platforms, while still retaining autonomy and control. To do this, we must lower the barrier to entry for users and developers alike. Tools, platforms, and systems in the IndieWeb ecosystem must be as simple to use as the corporate alternatives, if not simpler.</p><p></p><h3><strong>5. Building the IndieWeb Ecosystem: Decentralized, User-Centric, Ethical</strong></h3><p></p><p>To break the stranglehold of big tech, we need to build an ecosystem that is more compelling than the corporate web. This means developing tools that not only offer independence but are also genuinely easy to use. It means creating decentralized networks that don’t sacrifice user experience for control. And most of all, it means fostering a community that is not just about technology, but about ethics, values, and the long-term future of the web.</p><p></p><h4>5.1 Decentralized Identity and Content Ownership</h4><p></p><p>The foundation of the IndieWeb is decentralized identity and content ownership. Every user should control their own domain—whether that’s a personal website, blog, or another space on the web. This domain should be the single source of truth for their online presence. Instead of relying on platforms like Twitter or Facebook to host their content, users should own and control everything they create.</p><p></p><p>Web technologies like Webmentions, Microformats, and ActivityPub make it possible to decentralize social interactions as well. Users can post content on their own site and still interact with others across the web, without needing a centralized platform to mediate the interaction. This means we can build social networks without giving control over our identities or data to third parties.</p><p></p><h4>5.2 Ethical Design and Development</h4><p></p><p>Building a decentralized web is not just a technical challenge; it’s an ethical one. We must ensure that the systems and tools we create don’t replicate the problems of the corporate web. Surveillance, data exploitation, and algorithmic manipulation must be rejected outright. Instead, IndieWeb tools should be designed with user privacy, transparency, and consent at their core.</p><p></p><p>At the same time, we need to avoid creating overly complex systems that make participation in the IndieWeb exclusive or difficult. Simplicity and accessibility are key. The goal is to empower everyone—not just developers, but everyday users—to build and control their own web presence.</p><p></p><h4>5.3 A New Browser War: Ending Chromium’s Monopoly</h4><p></p><p>One of the key battlegrounds in the fight for a decentralized web will be the browser. As it stands, Google’s Chromium project underpins a vast majority of web browsers, including Chrome, Microsoft Edge, Opera, and others. This creates a monoculture where one company essentially sets the standards for how the web operates.</p><p></p><p>But there are new challengers on the horizon. Projects like the Ladybird browser aim to break the Chromium monopoly and bring diversity back to web standards. The success of these projects will be crucial in ensuring that the web remains an open, flexible, and user-controlled space, rather than a corporate-controlled silo.</p><p></p><h3><strong>6. A Call to Action: Building the Future We Want</strong></h3><p></p><p>The web is not doomed to remain a space dominated by corporate giants. The IndieWeb offers an alternative vision—one where individuals own their content, control their data, and shape their own digital experiences. But realizing this vision will require action on multiple fronts.</p><p></p><ul><li><strong>For users</strong>, it means making the conscious choice to leave behind the convenience of corporate platforms in favor of independence and freedom.</li></ul><p></p><ul><li><strong>For developers</strong>, it means building tools that prioritize user control, simplicity, and ethical design.</li></ul><p></p><ul><li><strong>For communities</strong>, it means fostering a culture that values autonomy, collaboration, and openness, while resisting the seductive pull of corporate ecosystems.</li></ul><p></p><p>The IndieWeb is not just a technical movement; it is a cultural and ethical one. We are fighting not just for a different kind of web, but for a different kind of relationship with technology—one that puts people first, not profits. This manifesto is a call to those who believe that the web can be more than a marketplace for attention, data, and manipulation. It can be a space for human connection, creativity, and freedom. But only if we make it so.</p><p></p><h3><strong>7. Conclusion: The Future is Ours to Build</strong></h3><p></p><p>The choice before us is clear. We can continue down the path of convenience, ceding control of our digital lives to a handful of powerful corporations, or we can take the harder, but far more rewarding, path toward independence. The IndieWeb is not about rejecting all technology or abandoning progress; it is about ensuring that the technology we build serves us—not the other way around.</p><p></p><p>If we want to reclaim the web, we must act now. We must reject convenience as an excuse for corporate control. We must build the tools, systems, and communities that will make the web a truly decentralized, user-owned space once again. The future of the web is in our hands. Let’s build it together.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/manifesto-of-the-indieweb-reclaiming-the-web-from-convenience-and-corporate-control.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/manifesto-of-the-indieweb-reclaiming-the-web-from-convenience-and-corporate-control.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 17:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Self-Hosting is a Game-Changer]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>In a world where every click is tracked, every data point sold, and every service locked behind a subscription, self-hosting is like finding a hidden door to freedom. It’s a rebellion against the idea that you need a tech giant to do anything online. And if you’re like me, running your own Matrix instance, Jellyfin server, and even a modded Minecraft server, you already know: self-hosting is where it’s at.</p><p></p><h2>Taking Back Control with Matrix</h2><p>Let’s talk about Matrix. If you haven’t heard of it, it’s an open standard for decentralized communication. Think of it as your own personal chat system, where you decide who gets to see what. No more worrying about Big Tech scanning your DMs or wondering if your data is being sold to the highest bidder.</p><p>By self-hosting Matrix, you’re not just using a chat app; you’re owning your communication. You get to decide how your data is handled, who has access to it, and even how the service is run. Plus, it’s just cool to say, “Hit me up on my Matrix server.” It’s a flex that says, “I’m in control here.”</p><p></p><h2>Jellyfin: Streaming Without the Strings</h2><p>Next up is Jellyfin, the open-source media server that puts Netflix to shame. Well, at least for everything that’s not on Netflix, Amazon Prime, or Disney+. But here’s the beauty of it: with Jellyfin, you’re not tied to any one platform. You don’t have to worry about your favorite show getting pulled or a random price hike because some execs need a new yacht.</p><p>Jellyfin lets you stream your own library of music, movies, and shows on your terms. You decide what’s in your collection, how it’s organized, and when it’s available. Plus, there’s no need to deal with those pesky subscription fees or annoying ads. And if you’re into customization, Jellyfin has you covered with its endless tweaking options.</p><p></p><h2>Modded Minecraft on thehaj.space: Building Worlds Your Way</h2><p>Let’s not forget about the modded Minecraft server over on thehaj.space. Hosting a Minecraft server is one thing, but hosting a modded server is like playing God in a universe where you write the rules. The vanilla game is fantastic, but mods take it to another level—whether you’re adding new dimensions, tinkering with complex tech mods, or just throwing in some ridiculous fun, mods transform Minecraft into something uniquely yours.</p><p>Running a modded Minecraft server means you control the experience entirely. You choose the mods, tailor the gameplay, and create a custom world that reflects your vision. And the best part? You get to share that world with friends, building a community around something you’ve crafted from the ground up. There’s nothing quite like the camaraderie that forms when everyone’s working together—or against each other—in a world that’s entirely your creation.</p><p></p><h2>Why Self-Hosting Matters</h2><p>Self-hosting is more than just a hobby; it’s a statement. It’s saying no to the idea that we have to rely on corporations to provide us with online services. It’s taking back control of our digital lives, one server at a time. Whether it’s for privacy, customization, or just the sheer joy of running things yourself, self-hosting is a way to carve out your own corner of the internet.</p><p>And let’s be real, there’s something badass about running your own services. It’s like being the captain of your own ship, navigating the digital seas with confidence and autonomy. You don’t just use the internet; you own a piece of it.</p><p>So, if you’re tired of being just another user in the corporate machine, consider self-hosting. Whether it’s a Matrix server, Jellyfin, or a modded Minecraft world, there’s no better way to experience the internet on your own terms. Trust me, once you start, you’ll wonder how you ever lived any other way.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-self-hosting-is-a-game-changer.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-self-hosting-is-a-game-changer.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 17:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[So I got this watch…]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>As a tech enthusiast who loves tinkering with gadgets, I was thrilled to discover the <strong>Watchy smartwatch</strong>. Unlike other smartwatches that lock me into a specific ecosystem, Watchy is a fully open-source device that gives me the freedom to customize and experiment to my heart’s content. Here’s why I think the Watchy smartwatch is so great and why it’s become my go-to wearable.</p><p></p><h2>Open-Source Freedom</h2><p></p><p>The biggest draw for me with Watchy is its open-source nature. Having complete access to both the software and hardware designs means that I can truly make this smartwatch my own. Unlike proprietary devices, Watchy allows me to dive into its operating system, modify code, and even create my own watch faces.</p><p></p><h3>Why Open Source Matters</h3><p></p><ol><li><strong>Community Collaboration</strong>: Being part of a vibrant community of developers and makers is incredibly rewarding. I’ve found countless customizations and enhancements contributed by others, and I can also share my creations with the community.</li></ol><p></p><ol><li><strong>Transparency</strong>: I appreciate knowing exactly what’s running on my device. With open source, there are no hidden processes or unexplained functionalities, giving me peace of mind about privacy and security.</li></ol><p></p><ol><li><strong>Future-Proof</strong>: The community support for Watchy means that even if the official updates slow down, new features and improvements can still be developed and shared among users.</li></ol><p></p><h2>Customizable Hardware</h2><p></p><p>Another aspect of Watchy that I love is its customizable hardware. It uses the ESP32 microcontroller, a popular and well-documented component in the DIY tech world. This choice opens up endless possibilities for hardware projects and modifications. I’ve enjoyed experimenting with different sensors and modules, allowing me to expand Watchy’s capabilities beyond what typical smartwatches offer.</p><p></p><h3>Personal Projects</h3><p></p><ul><li><strong>QR Code Display</strong>: One of my favorite projects is using Watchy to display QR codes. By programming the watch to show my Revolut QR code or my VCF contact card at the press of a button, I’ve turned it into a handy tool for quick and easy transactions or exchanging contact information.</li></ul><p></p><ul><li><strong>Unique Watch Faces</strong>: I’ve created my own watch faces to match my style and preferences, a fun way to personalize my wearable experience.</li></ul><p></p><h2>A Minimalist Design</h2><p></p><p>While the Watchy may not boast the sleek design of an Apple Watch, I appreciate its minimalist aesthetic. The e-paper display is easy on the eyes and offers excellent battery life, perfect for someone like me who values function over form. Its lightweight build makes it comfortable to wear all day long.</p><p></p><h2>The Learning Experience</h2><p></p><p>Using Watchy has been a fantastic learning experience. It’s not just a smartwatch; it’s a platform for exploration and creativity. Using Watchy has reignited my passion for embedded systems and electronics. It’s not just a smartwatch; it’s a platform for exploration and creativity, allowing me to apply my existing skills in new and exciting ways. I’ve enjoyed using Watchy to innovate and solve practical problems, which is something no off-the-shelf smartwatch would ever offer me.</p><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p></p><p>If you’re a maker, developer, or simply someone who loves customizing and learning through technology, the Watchy smartwatch is a fantastic choice. It’s a device that grows with you, encouraging creativity and innovation. I’ve enjoyed every moment of my journey with Watchy and can’t wait to see what new projects I’ll tackle next.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/so-i-got-this-watch.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/so-i-got-this-watch.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 17:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solving messaging problems with an audio messaging service]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>As some of you might have heard I’m currently working on a new service with a little team called voicenext which is an audio messaging service.</p><p></p><p>voicenext is a new way to communicate with your friends by using audio instead of text. For one this solves the most obvious problem: smartphone keyboards suck. It also solves a second problem which is getting the message across. Did you know there’s like 5 different ways to say “Hello” in German and depending on the tone it can mean different things? Now you know. And I bet this isn’t an exclusive problem to the German language either.</p><p></p><p>Now there’s a few problems to solve as well with voice notes. For example some people tend to send voice notes that are longer than a couple of minutes. I don’t know, but if you want to tell me so much wouldn’t it be easier to just call me? That’s why we limit voice notes to 30 seconds. We found this is a tolerable length for voice notes without compromising on content. Just skip your “uh”s and come straight to the point, done, we’re under 30 seconds.</p><p></p><p>Another issue we found is that voice notes don’t sound good, they’re either too low volume or there’s just a bunch of noise in the background. Next time your friend tries to fire up a nuke while sending a voice note tell them to use voicenext, their voice will be crystal clear.</p><p></p><p>Then there’s compression. As you might know compression is really awful. So how do we manage that your voice notes sound crystal clear while also not eating up too much data. Easy: use a compression algorithm that doesn’t make your voice sound absolutely awful. For that we use an industry standard OPUS algorithm with a bitrate that is the sweet spot between good quality and compression. Problem solved.</p><p></p><p>I hope I could give you a small insight on what we’re currently cooking up. Until next time 👋</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/solving-messaging-problems-with-an-audio-messaging-service.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/solving-messaging-problems-with-an-audio-messaging-service.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 18:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Homebrewing my 2DS]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h2>Rediscovering favourites</h2><p></p><p>My venture into homebrewing on the Nintendo 2DS began with a simple desire: to enjoy my favourite games once more. Armed with the knowledge that homebrewing offered a pathway to unlock the device’s full potential, I embarked on a journey of rediscovery.</p><p></p><h2>The world of Homebrew</h2><p></p><p>Homebrewing quickly revealed itself as an accessible and inviting realm. With comprehensive documentation and user-friendly tools at my disposal, I found myself navigating the world of custom firmware with ease. In no time, I was immersed in a vibrant community of fellow enthusiasts, all united by a shared passion for gaming exploration.</p><p></p><h2>Modding made easy</h2><p></p><p>Contrary to expectations, modding my Nintendo 2DS proved to be a straightforward and seamless process. Thanks to the wealth of resources available online, I encountered minimal resistance as I installed custom firmware and unlocked new functionalities. The system’s well-documented architecture and user-friendly tools made each step feel like a natural progression, rather than a daunting technical challenge.</p><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p></p><p>My journey into homebrewing on the Nintendo 2DS was a testament to the empowering nature of gaming exploration. Far from being a daunting technical endeavor, modding the system offered a seamless and enjoyable experience, facilitated by a supportive community and accessible resources. As I continue to explore the vast landscape of homebrewing, I am reminded of the boundless creativity and innovation that define the gaming community.</p><p></p><p>Stay tuned for future posts where I delve deeper into maximizing the Nintendo 2DS’s online functionality through community servers, unlocking its full potential for online gaming experiences.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/homebrewing-my-2ds.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/homebrewing-my-2ds.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Maybe the Punkt. MP02 isn’t really something for me]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>It may seem hypocritical to initially praise a device, only to quickly lose interest. However, this is a pattern I’ve noticed in myself; becoming obsessed with something new, only for my attention to wane within days. Currently, this cycle revolves around the Punkt. MP02. Let’s delve into why this device may not be the right fit for me.</p><p></p><h2>Design and Durability</h2><p>The Punkt. MP02’s minimalist design is appealing, but it lacks the robustness and sleekness of an iPhone. The iPhone’s design is not only visually stunning, but also practical, with its water and dust resistance. The Punkt. MP02, on the other hand, is more susceptible to damage due to its lack of protective features.</p><p></p><h2>Features and Usability</h2><p>While the Punkt. MP02 emphasizes simplicity, this often results in a lack of essential features. In comparison, the iPhone offers a comprehensive range of applications and functionalities that cater to different needs and lifestyles, covering everything from productivity to entertainment. The Punkt. MP02, however, only provides basic calling and texting, which might not be enough for many users.</p><p></p><h2>Price Value</h2><p>When it comes to price value, the Punkt. MP02 is a hard sell. Despite its high cost, it offers far less functionality than an iPhone. Considering the vast array of features and the superior design quality that an iPhone offers, it’s clear that it provides better value for the price.</p><p></p><h2>Customizability</h2><p>Unlike the iPhone, which offers extensive personalization options through various phone cases, settings, apps, and widgets, the Punkt. MP02 is quite rigid, providing only basic settings and options.</p><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>Although the iPhone is more complex, it provides a more comprehensive and robust experience compared to the Punkt. MP02. Despite offering a unique and minimalist alternative to smartphones, the Punkt. MP02 falls short in terms of durability, features, and price value. These factors are worth considering if you’re thinking about switching.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/maybe-the-punkt-mp02-isn-t-really-something-for-me.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/maybe-the-punkt-mp02-isn-t-really-something-for-me.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 18:31:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shifting to a more minimal life with the Punkt. MP02]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I just shut down every server I own, got rid of any messaging app that was too much and really drove everyone to Signal. Yes, I like Signal again, it’s a reliable service and I think the Punkt. MP02 will be the device that will surely complete my last task of the mission. The mission to make my life less dependant on technology. So why trusting your phone when you can and make it a tethering device for your ThinkPad instead?</p><p></p><p>I have minimized the amount of apps on my iPhone already and will continue to do so until I collected every single-use device for that shift towards a more technology-free world. This doesn’t mean I cannot sit down and answer e-mails and Discord pings afterwards, I will take my time every evening for that, but I will not answer anything else than my phone during work hours, because that’s pretty much the only way to tell me that your matter is important for me. Also I kind of want to embrace a more minimalist lifestyle, because it seems to have made my life much more happier.</p><p></p><p>Right now my online banking needs a TAN device and I also have to order a chip card for the train subscription so I can successfully complete my mission. Once those two things are out of the way I can slowly shift to the Punkt. MP02 by the end of the year. This device will only allow me to make and receive phone calls, send and receive SMS, the same things for Signal and an option to tether my current connection to my backpack ThinkPad. I carry it around anywhere anyway so why not use it on the go?</p><p></p><p>In the meantime I will get used to that more minimal lifestyle as it’s healthier for me. Also I don’t have many meltdowns as I used to, not sinking into TikTok all day really helps my mental health. You should try that as well. Shut off your phone for a while and see what the world has to offer.</p><p></p><p>As the founder of Punkt. already said:</p><p></p><blockquote>If anyone wants to talk to me, they can give me a call. Other forms of communication, for example email or social media, are available when I choose to use them – and via a linked device that allows me to use them more effectively.</blockquote><p></p><p>And I really share the same vision. I will answer you when I chose that it’s best for me, not the other way around. Otherwise, just give me a call.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/shifting-to-a-more-minimal-life-with-the-punkt-mp02.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/shifting-to-a-more-minimal-life-with-the-punkt-mp02.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 18:32:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Empowering the Web – Mastodon and the Fediverse for Digital Democracy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>The internet, once hailed as the great equalizer, has in recent years faced challenges to its democratic ideals. Social media giants monopolize the digital landscape, influencing narratives and controlling the flow of information. In response to this, a <strong>beacon of hope emerges: Mastodon and the fediverse</strong>, heralding a new era of democratized web interactions.</p><p></p><h2>Breaking the Chains of Centralization</h2><p></p><p>Traditional social media platforms operate under a centralized model, giving a handful of corporations unparalleled control over user data and content. <strong>Mastodon, a part of the fediverse, challenges this norm</strong>. Its decentralized structure means that no single entity dictates the rules, fostering an environment where users have a say in the platform’s evolution.</p><p></p><h2>User Empowerment Through Instance Autonomy</h2><p></p><p><strong>Mastodon instances, or servers, allow users to create and join communities</strong> based on shared interests. This decentralization not only prevents the concentration of power but also enables users to choose the environment that aligns with their values. It’s a stark departure from the one-size-fits-all approach of mainstream platforms.</p><p></p><h2>Inclusivity and Global Connectivity</h2><p></p><p><strong>The fediverse, a network of interconnected servers, extends beyond Mastodon to include various platforms like Akkoma and Friendica</strong>. This diversity enhances inclusivity, as users on different servers can still interact seamlessly. By transcending platform boundaries, the fediverse fosters global conversations, breaking down the walls that traditional social media often builds.</p><p></p><h2>No More Algorithmic Echo Chambers</h2><p></p><p><strong>Algorithms on mainstream platforms tend to create echo chambers</strong>, reinforcing existing beliefs and limiting exposure to diverse perspectives. <strong>Mastodon’s chronological timeline and open API allow users to see content in a more straightforward manner</strong>, avoiding the pitfalls of algorithmic bias. This promotes a healthier exchange of ideas and minimizes the risk of misinformation.</p><p></p><h2>Community Moderation and Content Control</h2><p></p><p><strong>The power to moderate content is often concentrated in the hands of a few on centralized platforms</strong>. <strong>Mastodon’s community-driven moderation distributes this authority among users</strong>. Each instance can set its own rules, empowering communities to define acceptable behavior. This approach ensures that moderation aligns with the values of the users rather than a distant corporate entity.</p><p></p><h2>Data Ownership and Privacy</h2><p></p><p><strong>Mastodon prioritizes user privacy by giving individuals control over their data</strong>. In a world where data is often exploited, this commitment to privacy is a refreshing change. Users can choose instances that align with their privacy preferences, giving them the freedom to participate without sacrificing personal information.</p><p></p><h2>Challenges and the Road Ahead</h2><p></p><p>While Mastodon and the fediverse present a promising vision of a democratized web, challenges remain. <strong>Widespread adoption and overcoming the inertia of established social media giants are formidable tasks</strong>. However, the momentum toward decentralization suggests a growing awareness of the importance of reclaiming control over our digital experiences.</p><p></p><p><strong>In conclusion, Mastodon and the fediverse embody the principles of a democratized web</strong>. By dismantling the centralized structures that dominate social media, these platforms empower users, promote inclusivity, and ensure a more democratic online space. <strong>As we navigate the evolving digital landscape, the fediverse stands as a beacon, beckoning towards a future where the internet truly belongs to the people</strong>.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/empowering-the-web-mastodon-and-the-fediverse-for-digital-democracy.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/empowering-the-web-mastodon-and-the-fediverse-for-digital-democracy.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 18:33:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[mastodon.art is not a safespace]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><em>This blog post is a direct answer to disprove to mastodon.art’s statement about it being a safespace which you can read here: <a href="https://dotart.blog/dotart-blog/dotart-as-a-safe-space-instance">https://dotart.blog/dotart-blog/dotart-as-a-safe-space-instance</a>. I will quote some passages and giving an answer from the standpoint of an instance admin that has lost the battle against a big instance spreading lies and misinformation about federation and the fediverse community. This reply is written to Welsh Pixie who probably wrote the post and is in charge of mastodon.art.</em></p><p></p><blockquote>dotART may be an art instance, but our full and primary purpose is to provide a safe space for marginalised folk who also happen to do creative work. To this end, we have strong policies that shape the vibe of our community and allow our community to thrive in a harassment-free environment.</blockquote><p></p><p>This is fully understandable, my instance also had those policies in place. I am sure, that this is what most of the fediverse is doing.</p><p></p><blockquote>We have harsh defederation policies where we will defederate from any instance that we (the .art mod team) feel is a threat to the safety of our community; this can be for a variety of reasons, including being a far-right/conspiracy theory/‘free speech’ instance, not taking a hard stance against hate speech, poor moderation that enables trolling, etc.</blockquote><p></p><p>Okay, this is quite ironic, because my instance was blocked for apparently poor moderation. Me and my team made sure the moderation policies were enforced and we made sure that we defederated from instances that would actively harm our community. Is absturztau.be far-right just because that instance doesn’t run Mastodon? Is qoto.org too ”free speech” despite actively moderating against hateful content? I am not sure what this should be a reference to, but I am quite certain that there is still a lot of instances that should be re-reviewed with an objective standpoint.</p><p></p><blockquote>We adopt a proactive style to moderation and defederation that, wherever possible, allows us to prevent harassment rather than to deal with it after it has already taken place. We don’t demand other instances do things our way – one of the great things about the fediverse is that anyone can run their instance any way they like, and people can join instances with moderation styles that best fit the experience they want from their social media.</blockquote><p></p><p>You tend to overblock, you don’t defederate with bad instances. This is different and you won’t even admit it. Sure you don’t demand other instances to do moderation ”your way”, but you don’t want to admit, that mastodon.art has grown so big that other instances have to follow suit or they will get blocked as well and lose a ton of good content on their instance. Being unable to follow Daniela Schreiter (she’s doing amazing content about autism and I even have a few of her books) or the Krita project is not only inconvenient, but also heartbreaking to see, because those people indirectly support someone that is so overprotective, that you can’t interact with the wider fediverse anymore. <strong>Defederation should be the last option if you consider someone not aligning with your own moderation policies. Please first try to establish a dialog between you and the admins before considering a defederation AND ask your own community what they would think about it before they can’t access their content the next day.</strong></p><p></p><blockquote>For example, we have some of the journalist instances limited because the people in our community are the people who are often treated incredibly poorly in journalism, and it should be their call whether or not they want to ineract with journalists. This is very specific to the vibe of our instance, but doesn’t apply universally to all instances.</blockquote><p></p><p>You are probably talking about journa.host. I don’t know what led to this decision, but journa.host never harassed anyone to this day. This is again your own decision to block this instance, driven by your own beliefs and not what your community asked you to do. An instance with that size shouldn’t pressure their own beliefs onto someone which doesn’t mean that I am endorsing allowing hateful content at a given instance size. I know that fake journalism like BILD (a very famous and awful newspaper in Germany) is harmful to people, because they often put things out of context and discredit people by doing that, but from my understanding, journa.host explicitly states that such content is not allowed in their platform. Also see your own instance as a news site, because I have often seen you and your users discredit anyone that is just a little bit different than mastodon.art by using the instance’s reach to their advantage. This shouldn’t be an issue, but you make it one and you have never fixed it.</p><p></p><blockquote>dotART has a reputation for ‘blocking everybody’, but the fediverse is huge. There are over 23,000 instances (https://fedidb.org). The biggest one, mastodon.social, who we don’t block, has over 1.3 million total users. Our block list has 1024 instances on it (not all of them are blocks, either – some of them are just limits, and a big chunk of them are instances full of Twitter mirrors), and a huge number of them are tiny single-user or ‘one person and a few of their friends’ instances. The majority of our blocks are also instances who are well known for actively harassing people on instances that don’t block them. There are also many, many instances that block much heavier than we do – but because we’re big, we get noticed when we take moderation actions.</blockquote><p></p><p>Okay, here is a lot to unpack. That list doesn’t respect the active servers count, meaning most of these 23k servers sure still run, but they are basically a ghost town, set up once and forgotten. By the end of koyu.space we federated with around 10k active instances, your instance was responsible for about less than the half of the public content. This means once you blocked us a huge fraction of publicly accessible content was gone from our instance. Your instance also doesn’t ”block everybody”, I agree here, but you block a huge fraction of the active fediverse. Putting your own decisions over your own users is not what the fediverse is about, this is why user-level moderation tools exist as well, but your job as an admin should make the process for your users easier. Next time if you consider overblocking just put your instance in allow list mode. Apparently now you understand that your instance is big, but I don’t think you still know what the exact consequences to these actions are. I think you should realize that the consequences are that you put your instance at risk breaking apart the more you try to defederate, especially when the block was unjustified. We couldn’t get in touch with you since you never replied, so we don’t even know what you actually blocked koyu.space for as ”channery” (whatever that is) and ”anti-moderation” are made up reasons.</p><p></p><blockquote>Most of the people in our community join our instance specifically because of the way we run it. They join via word of mouth from people telling their friends that this is a safe space. People who face unjust discrimination and who are ostracised by society can exist on our instance with thousands of other people who are both like them and also wonderfully different.</blockquote><p></p><p>No, they don’t, it’s the second part. People join, because mastodon.art is big and everyone else tells them to join that instance. It’s not, because it’s a safe space, it’s rather, because your instance is big and no one cares about the details. Your users actively harassed me and my team members on koyu.space for reasons you don’t even want to explain to us.</p><p></p><blockquote>We get messages every day from our dotART-ists telling us they appreciate how we run the community, and we get overwhelming support from our community for the moderation decisions we make. We also don’t hold a grudge over people who might want to leave our instance because it’s too restrictive (and, in fact, encourage people to seek out a community that best fits them!) – again, the great thing about the fediverse is it allows for a multitude of communities that are managed in different styles and that suit a variety of needs.</blockquote><p></p><p>This is nice and I think this is also why running a fediverse server is worth it. You can surround yourself with a bunch of nice people. The problem is you actually hold a grudge over people who want to leave your friend’s instances. So people who don’t think you should be in charge of running mastodon.art are getting harassed and blocked without further explanation, because for whatever reason you can’t take valid criticism.</p><p></p><blockquote>So, if you’re on mastodon.art, that’s the kind of experience you will get. We appreciate it’s not for everybody, but it’s not meant to be for everybody. It’s meant to be for the people who most need this kind of safety from social media.</blockquote><p></p><p>Your instance is not a safe space and you have proven it multiple times outside of your own instance, so I don’t think you can make sure the experience is better inside. My experience with mastodon.art was that once we slightly criticize you and your behavior we would instantly receive the ban hammer without explanation, getting harassed by you and your own users and lose thousands of people posting great content.</p><p></p><p>I don’t think you should run a Mastodon instance at all and stay where you originally came from, Twitter is your home and Mastodon was better without your instance. You pose a threat to the fediverse as you are not familiar with fediverse culture in general. We people have a history on here and we don’t need another person that tells anyone what software to use, what language to speak or what operating system to run. We are all adults and we care about each other and you are clearly not caring about the people of this network if you are trying to EEE (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embrace,_extend,_and_extinguish">embrace, extend, extinguish</a>) your way through it and force your policies onto every server owner.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/mastodon-art-is-not-a-safespace.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/mastodon-art-is-not-a-safespace.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 17:34:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reflecting on my journey as a Mastodon admin – Prioritizing self-care and growth]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>As an administrator of a Mastodon instance, I embarked on a mission to create a safe and inclusive online space for users. However, the weight of responsibility and the demands of server administration took a toll on my well-being. In sharing my experience, I hope to shed light on the challenges faced by Mastodon admins and the importance of prioritizing self-care and personal growth.</p><p></p><p>Administering a Mastodon instance comes with numerous challenges. The constant need for server maintenance, security measures, and scalability can be overwhelming. Balancing the expectations of the community, handling abusive content, and making difficult decisions takes a toll on one’s passion and dedication.</p><p></p><p>Over time, I realized that I needed to prioritize my own well-being. Instead of ignoring the signs of burnout, I viewed it as an opportunity for personal growth and self-reflection. Recognizing the importance of self-care, I began to set boundaries, take breaks, and seek support from the community.</p><p></p><p>Additionally, the introduction of the revamped trends feature by Eugen, the creator of Mastodon, added further complexity to my role as an admin. While new features can enhance the user experience and attract more engagement, they also demanded additional attention and resources to ensure they were implemented effectively.</p><p></p><p>As an admin, I found myself grappling with the challenge of balancing the demands of managing the Mastodon instance, addressing user concerns, and staying abreast of the latest feature updates. The constant need to adapt to these changes and allocate time and resources to understand and implement them put additional strain on my already limited capacity.</p><p></p><p>While I appreciated the efforts made by Eugen and the Mastodon development team to improve the platform, the rapid introduction of new features without sufficient preparation or support for admins could inadvertently contribute to burnout. It is crucial for developers to consider the impact on admins and provide the necessary resources and documentation to ease the transition and ensure smooth implementation.</p><p></p><p>Moving forward, it is my hope that there will be a stronger collaboration between Mastodon developers and admins to foster an environment where new features can be implemented effectively, taking into account the time and support required by admins to adapt and manage them successfully. By working together, we can create a more sustainable and supportive ecosystem that benefits both the Mastodon community and its dedicated administrators.</p><p></p><p>Furthermore, while striving to create an inclusive and welcoming space, I encountered the challenge of navigating the complexity of dealing with individuals who did not understand the balancing act between free expression and the responsibility to maintain a safe environment. The toxicity of some users, who disregarded the guidelines and principles of inclusivity, created significant issues within my Mastodon instance.</p><p></p><p>Despite my efforts to enforce community guidelines and foster respectful dialogue, a subset of individuals persisted in spreading hate speech, harassment, and harmful content. This not only undermined the well-being of other users but also put immense pressure on me as an admin to address these issues promptly and effectively.</p><p></p><p>The toxic behavior of these individuals not only disrupted the community but also attracted negative attention to my instance. The constant battles to moderate and combat toxicity took an emotional toll, leaving me exhausted and disheartened.</p><p></p><p>In some instances, the toxicity escalated to the point where my instance faced cancellation or significant backlash from the wider Mastodon community. Dealing with the aftermath of such events added further strain and complications, as I had to navigate the repercussions while striving to maintain a supportive and inclusive environment for the remaining users.</p><p></p><p>It became evident that addressing toxicity required a multifaceted approach. In addition to enforcing clear guidelines and moderation practices, fostering open and respectful communication with the community became vital. By engaging with users, actively listening to their concerns, and taking appropriate action, I aimed to create a collaborative atmosphere where everyone felt heard and valued.</p><p></p><p>Moving forward, I recognize the need to continuously educate and raise awareness about the importance of inclusivity and responsible online behavior. Implementing stronger measures to combat toxic behavior and involving the community in decision-making processes can contribute to a healthier and more constructive Mastodon experience.</p><p></p><p>To my fellow admins who have faced similar challenges, I extend my empathy and support. It is crucial to remember that the toxic behavior of a few individuals does not define the community as a whole. By standing firm in our commitment to inclusivity, while taking necessary actions to address toxicity, we can continue to build resilient and thriving Mastodon instances that uphold the values of respect, diversity, and free expression within the appropriate bounds.</p><p></p><p>The toxicity of some individuals who failed to grasp the distinction between free speech and responsible expression had a detrimental impact on my Mastodon instance. Addressing these issues required significant efforts in moderation, community engagement, and education. By actively working towards creating an inclusive environment and combating toxicity, we can safeguard the integrity and well-being of our Mastodon communities.</p><p></p><p>In addition to the challenges mentioned earlier, my Mastodon instance encountered a series of database crashes that had severe consequences, including the loss of valuable user data. These incidents had a significant impact on the overall functioning of the platform and the trust of our user community.</p><p></p><p>Database crashes can occur due to a variety of reasons, such as hardware failures, software glitches, or power outages. Despite implementing backup measures, the crashes often led to data loss, and the restoration process was not always successful. This meant that valuable user profiles, posts, and interactions were permanently erased, resulting in frustration and disappointment for our users.</p><p></p><p>Furthermore, the susceptibility of Mastodon to index corruption exacerbated the data loss issue. Index corruption occurs when the database indexes become corrupted or inconsistent, leading to performance issues and potential data inaccessibility. In some instances, even the backup measures were affected by index corruption, rendering them unreliable for data recovery purposes.</p><p></p><p>Dealing with these challenges was a humbling experience as an admin. It highlighted the importance of robust backup strategies and regular database maintenance. It became evident that relying solely on standard backup procedures was not enough to safeguard against potential data loss.</p><p></p><p>To mitigate the risk of future incidents, it is crucial for Mastodon admins to prioritize database integrity and invest in additional measures. Implementing more frequent backups, conducting routine database checks and optimizations, and exploring alternative storage solutions can enhance data protection and reduce the impact of crashes and index corruption.</p><p></p><p>It is also essential to establish clear communication channels with the Mastodon community in the event of data loss. Transparently informing users about the challenges faced and the steps being taken to mitigate the impact can help maintain trust and alleviate concerns.</p><p></p><p>The occurrence of database crashes, data loss, and index corruption can significantly disrupt the operation of a Mastodon instance and cause frustration for users. As admins, it is our responsibility to prioritize database integrity, implement robust backup strategies, and communicate effectively with the community during such incidents. By learning from these challenges and taking proactive measures, we can strive to create a more resilient and reliable Mastodon environment for the benefit of all users.</p><p></p><p>Despite the difficulties I encountered as a Mastodon admin, my journey has instilled in me a deep appreciation for the power and potential of the Fediverse. I remain hopeful that the failures and shortcomings of centralized platforms like Twitter and, more recently, Reddit will introduce more people to the decentralized and inclusive nature of the Fediverse. I am grateful for the opportunities to learn, grow, and contribute to this remarkable community. Moving forward, I am excited to continue supporting the Fediverse, fostering a safe and vibrant space for users to connect, express themselves, and embrace the values of inclusivity and free expression. Together, we can shape a future where the Fediverse thrives as a beacon of hope and an alternative to the limitations of traditional social media platforms.</p><p></p><p>To my fellow Mastodon admins, I urge you to prioritize your well-being, set boundaries, and seek support when needed. Remember that your journey is not solely about instance administration but also about personal growth and maintaining a healthy balance. Together, we can create a stronger and more sustainable Mastodon community that thrives on the principles of inclusivity and free expression.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/reflecting-on-my-journey-as-a-mastodon-admin-prioritizing-self-care-and-growth.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/reflecting-on-my-journey-as-a-mastodon-admin-prioritizing-self-care-and-growth.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 17:35:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mastodon’s legacy on the internet]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Mastodon has been a huge success last year and I think the success is going to increase even further. After Elon Musk has locked out all prominent Twitter developers most of them quickly switched to Mastodon for their development platform of choice.</p><p></p><p>This resulted in a plethora of new apps that quickly gained traction on the internet. This leads to a significant increase in the number of news outlets to report about it and bringing more developers onboard.</p><p></p><p>Developers like Tapbots or Buffer replaced what Twitter had to offer as a platform before Musk’s hostile takeover. It’s those developers that made Twitter nice to use and Mastodon buttons, embeds and references are slowly becoming the standard instead of Twitter’s own tools and widgets.</p><p></p><p>It’s a chain reaction that started with simply making a platform unusable and force their developers to switch, and in return their users.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/mastodon-s-legacy-on-the-internet.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/mastodon-s-legacy-on-the-internet.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 18:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The EU’s thoughts about Messenger interoperability is good if handled correctly]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>The EU wants to make messaging services like WhatsApp, Telegram, Facebook Messenger, Teams, Element, Signal etc. interoperable meaning that a seemless communication between those services would be possible. This sounds great at first, because you only need one app and nothing else, but if not handled correctly this might end up in the same mess we’re finding us in today. Cryptocurrencies can’t be the answer as well <a href="https://leonie.lgbt/why-ai-cryptocurrency-metaverse-and-all-that-crap-doesnt-matter/">for obvious reasons</a>.</p><p></p><h2>Introducing Matrix</h2><p></p><p><a href="https://matrix.org">Matrix</a> does one thing differently than the others: federation and bridging. You can literally bridge all your favourite chat apps into one app and have only one app that rules them all. It’s also fairly <a href="https://t2bot.io">easy</a> to set up. If you’re hosting your own server, hosting a bridge is as easy as setting up a Docker container and add one line to a config file.</p><p></p><h2>Why Matrix?</h2><p></p><p>Matrix has been in use in governments for a long time and individual users can try it out as well. The problem is that there’s no way to convince the average user switching away from centralised messaging platforms like WhatsApp. Full data suvereignity ensures data protection, security and privacy. Also it’s kinda cool telling your friends that you host a messaging platform.</p><p></p><h2>State surveillance</h2><p></p><p>Since most of those messaging services aren’t end-to-end encrypted – or misleadingly claim end-to-end encryption – using Matrix would enforce end-to-end encryption. Safely backing up your keys would also work since Matrix also allows that. This ensures nobody on earth (including governments) can read your chats.</p><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p></p><p>The EU wanting to make messaging services to interoperate sounds like a great idea if it doesn’t get lobbied to hell with protocols nobody uses or wants to use. Matrix might be the answer to our “I have 20 messaging apps for 20 people”-problem if the EU ever considers that as an official standard.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-eu-s-thoughts-about-messenger-interoperability-is-good-if-handled-correctly.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-eu-s-thoughts-about-messenger-interoperability-is-good-if-handled-correctly.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 18:38:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Speeding Up Linux Startup and Shutdown]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>In this post I’m running down different ways to speed up your Linux system.</p><p></p><h2>Running a kernel with less modules</h2><p></p><p>This requires some advanced tinkering with kernel configurations and all that fun stuff and intended for advanced users only. Running my system with a custom kernel didn’t bring me any noticable differences in terms of speed and performance, but general load slightly improved.</p><p></p><h2>Using systemd to eliminate services that start for too long</h2><p></p><p>With <code>sudo systemd-analyze blame</code> you can see what services take the longest to start up.</p><p></p><p><code>[koyu@luna ~]$ sudo systemd-analyze blame<br/>7.077s plymouth-quit-wait.service<br/>6.332s NetworkManager-wait-online.service</code><br/></p><p></p><p>So disabling <code>plymouth-quit-wait.service</code> and <code>NetworkManager-wait-online.service</code> would improve startup times by a whopping 13 seconds! Check your system and see how much more seconds you can save each time you boot up your Linux box.</p><p></p><h2>Cutting service stop times</h2><p></p><p>Usually my system shuts off in three seconds so waiting around three seconds for a service to shut down should be sufficient, everything above that gets brutally killed anyway and the system shuts down. Not very recommended and many people might cringe, but this helped improve shut down times especially when some crappy service was hanging the whole shutdown sequence. Search for the line <code>DefaultTimeoutStopSec=90s</code> and adjust it to your liking in the following config files:</p><ul><li>/etc/systemd/system.conf</li><li>/etc/systemd/user.conf</li></ul><p></p><h2>Using EFISTUB instead of a bootloader</h2><p></p><p>If supported EFISTUB loads your kernel directly using your EFI chip. This is great, because you don’t need a bootloader then that searches for everything that’s required to boot up your system. Depending on your distribution it’s a different experience. On Arch you simply install <code>efistubmgr-git</code> from the AUR which is a EFISTUB management tool written by an old friend of mine. I wonder what that guy does these days.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/speeding-up-linux-startup-and-shutdown.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/speeding-up-linux-startup-and-shutdown.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 18:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Security notice: Vidar Stealer abuses the Mastodon social network]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>One of Vidar’s unique behaviors is in obtaining dynamic configuration and C2 connectivity. Once executed, Vidar’s first step is to receive its configuration, by abusing the Mastodon social network.</p><p>Mastodon, is an open-source social network that imitates Twitter on many levels. Recent cases suggest that threat actors set up social profiles in Mastodon as a communication channel with the stealers. The social profiles don’t contain much more than a random post. The description of the profile contains the IP of the C2 the stealer should communicate with to receive configuration, dependency files and the location to which to upload its stolen data.</p><p>Vidar connects to a predefined user within the Mastodon network via an HTTPS protocol so it can access the C2 IP for further instructions.</p><p>[block]vidar-stealer[/block]</p><p>Highlighted from <a href="https://cyberint.com/blog/research/vidar-stealer-abuses-mastadon-social-network/">https://cyberint.com/blog/research/vidar-stealer-abuses-mastadon-social-network/</a></p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/security-notice-vidar-stealer-abuses-the-mastodon-social-network.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/security-notice-vidar-stealer-abuses-the-mastodon-social-network.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 18:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is GNOME really that bad?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>After I stumbled upon <a href="https://dataswamp.org/~solene/2021-11-10-how-I-ended-liking-gnome.html">solene’s blog post</a> about GNOME and accessibility I also wanted to say what I personally think about GNOME as well.</p><p></p><h2>A solid desktop</h2><p></p><p>Yes, you might say extensions will break the desktop from time to time, but there are things that will keep you from having this issue and actually have a solid desktop experience. I use Fedora and they support the last two releases of GNOME which is enough time for developers to keep up with adjusting their extensions to the new version. Also everything is integrated into GNOME, it’s an outright solid user experience right from the beginning, especially on Fedora.</p><p></p><h2>Everything you need</h2><p></p><p>GNOME comes with a variety of applications to get stuff done. What I like especially is their e-mail client Evolution mail which not only snuggly integrates into the desktop, but also supports modern functions out of the box without having to hack them in along with full Exchange and PGP support.</p><p></p><h2>What is the point in “removing features”?</h2><p></p><p>This isn’t removing features really, they rather get moved into a seperate extension than clogging up the desktop. I think of GNOME more as a base system to build your specific user experience and user interface changes on top. If you want to extend your desktop just add extensions to match your workflow.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/is-gnome-really-that-bad.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/is-gnome-really-that-bad.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 18:35:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Facebook down? Why decentralisation matters]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Facebook went down today and this got me thinking. The fediverse which is decentralised and opposes itself as an alternative to the centralized magasites like Facebook doesn’t seem to have a problem like this.</p><p></p><h2>What is decentralization?</h2><p></p><p>Decentralization is the concept of not having a central authority controlling all in- and outgoing transactions. In less broader terms this means that while Facebook is owned and controlled by Mark Zuckerberg and his gang, decentralised networks like the fediverse are owned and operated by the people for the people. This means if one node fails it wouldn’t bring the whole network down and completely ruin all of your communications.</p><p></p><blockquote>This means if one node fails it wouldn’t bring the whole network down and completely ruin all of your communications.</blockquote><p></p><p>Read: <a href="https://leonie.lgbt/2021/10/04/facebook-down-why-decentralisation-matters/a-quick-introduction-to-the-fediverse/">A quick introduction to the fediverse</a></p><p></p><h2>But why does it matter then?</h2><p></p><p>I think it matters in the terms of why we should trust a single person with all of our data. Do you want to let your communications depend on someone who lives somewhere in America and is essentially a total stranger? I think individual people like your IT specialist next door you call when you infested your computer with toolbars are a lot more trustworthy than some random people on earth. Also if you really want to start digging you’d just read the documentation and get your server set up by yourself.</p><p></p><p>Read: <a href="https://leonie.lgbt/2021/10/04/facebook-down-why-decentralisation-matters/how-to-plan-and-host-a-mastodon-instance/">How to plan and host a Mastodon instance</a></p><p></p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p></p><p>I wonder why people still want to depend all of their communication on one singular entity which is definitely prone to fail. Such people are still a mystery to me.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/facebook-down-why-decentralisation-matters.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/facebook-down-why-decentralisation-matters.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 17:34:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why NFTs, Metaverse and all that doesn’t matter]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Let me start this off with saying that all the buzzwords that have been a thing the last few years are worth nothing and let me say why this is.</p><p></p><h2>Cryptocurrencies don’t help the web, it destroys it</h2><p></p><p>The web was originally thought as you input information and get information back, just like how computers work, but with the idea that this can be done remotely. So let’s say you want to request a site containing your favourite apple pie recipe your grandma made. If you noted it down somewhere in the web it will stay there as long as a server is up. Now let’s say everyone was using some random blockchain technology rather than the web. Your blockchain technology will crawl on its last legs if nobody will use it anymore, it’s like little webs constantly collapsing merely making it out of its development phase. Cryptocurrencies and NFTs are toys. Nothing else.</p><p></p><h2>The Metaverse can’t be the future, at least for now</h2><p></p><p>I don’t know what’s up with the Metaverse, but I’m not a fan of a random dude like Mark Zuckerberg being able to control what I can see through my Oculus goggles. Sure <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-59083601">Meta aka Facebook</a> has the technology to realize a Metaverse, but I don’t think they will actually be the ones doing it. Not only do they have some hefty law suits heading their way, but also I don’t think they will have the knowledge to compete in the Metaverse business in any way after multiple failed attempts to position themselves to gamers which would be the main target audience for these things. Also if there isn’t a specific way to have your privacy in that metaverse and no W3C-approved protocols it will meet the same fate as the blockchain. They are built to be doomed.</p><p></p><h2>NFTs are no proof of ownership</h2><p></p><p>Another myth I’m trying to debunk is that there’s no way to proof ownership through an NFT (non fungible token). It has the same energy as me sending you a random string of numbers and tell you this string represents my ownership of let’s say your house. This is not how copyright works either. I can’t proof my ownership on something through a random string of characters, it still has to backlink to the original work to be accepted and I have to be the actual owner of that item. So basically NFTs are just like fancy in-game cosmetics. They are worth nothing other than looking shiny and you don’t have the right to copyright them.</p><p></p><h2>Is this the future?</h2><p></p><p>Do you want to live in a future where you are not sure if you own the things you have on the web and where you can’t control what you physically see or experience? Me neither, so stop advocating and using NFTs or the Metaverse. I hope the bubble will burst at some point like any other blockchain technology or useless product venture capital has brought to life.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-nfts-metaverse-and-all-that-doesn-t-matter.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-nfts-metaverse-and-all-that-doesn-t-matter.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2021 17:33:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Creative expression through Fortnite]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Fortnite is my favourite game, I say that unironically. With their creative mode which has been a thing for a while now a lot of people can create custom maps where they can play with their friends or hang out on. You can even publish your map through a map code which you can pass along to people.</p><p></p><p>These are actually pretty nice reasons for people who aren’t just into battle royale right now. Fortnite isn’t just a battle-royale game anymore (it never was to begin with), but rather a way to hang out with your friends and have fun with them. I could even think about the creative mode getting used in the educational sector, because with creative maps you could also teach a lot of things. It kind of is its own type of media.</p><p></p><p>Fortnite really grew from a “game that a few kids play” to something useful yet fun. It’s really like Animal Crossing a virtual place to hang out with friends. There are even <a href="https://youtu.be/aSaW2V1Zi1k">entire music videos</a> created in Fortnite.</p><p></p><p>You can play Fortnite today on PC or Console for free. It’s a great game and I recommend everyone to check it out.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/creative-expression-through-fortnite.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/creative-expression-through-fortnite.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 17:32:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windows 11…]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Where should I even start, I’m disappointed…really disappointed. When I tried Windows 11 in a virtual machine it looked like it could be the next Windows XP or Windows 7. Instead it turned out that you can’t really get Windows 11 to run, even on fairly modern machines. This brings a lot of problems with it I’ll discuss in this article.</p><p></p><h2>The e-waste problem</h2><p></p><p>E-waste has been troubling us for decades now since technology existed. When computers were new nobody was thinking about potential environmentally dangerous things that’s inside of any computer. Windows computers were never built to last, because with each release Microsoft is putting the bar one higher on the system requirements. Surely any computer that’s modern could run Windows 11 perfectly fine, but the biggest issue is that Microsoft is deliberately whitelisting a very tiny fraction of computer parts out there. This doesn’t only make consumers want to buy a new PC, but also produces a lot of e-waste, because you’re throwing away your whole computer fleet for an operating system that would technically be supported on those computers you have thrown away. I could have also made the argument, that packaging the Windows operating system also produces some amount of waste, but Microsoft kind of learned that people could download ISOs off the internet and flash them onto USB sticks they already own. The problem is that Microsoft just went one step backwards with Windows 11 by removing a way to download ISO files and either forcing people to buy a boxed version or a PC preloaded with Windows 11. If you care about not being burned to death by dragging summer heats (and climate change is real) then I’d recommend that your next PC should run Linux instead, because for this you won’t need an entirely new computer.</p><p></p><h2>DRM and more</h2><p></p><p>In general I have nothing against people excercising their right to not have their works stolen, but in the case of Microsoft it’s a completely different story. Actively hindering people to customize, refine or otherwise make the experience better is a crime against humanity. What do I mean specifically? This means that Windows 11 really tries to first make secure boot mandantory. We may not know if there will be machines locked only to run Windows, but this is against any defintion of what a computer should be. Users should have the freedom to run any program they wish on a computer, this especially includes operating systems. Also Microsoft is actively encouraging people into buying more shitty DRM services like the Adobe Creative Cloud right through their DRM-infested store front, the Microsoft Store. There is no more such disgusting thing than putting hurdles in place for something people invested real money in.</p><p></p><h2>Are you even trying?</h2><p></p><p>Now we just talked about the technical aspects (or at least the glimpse of what I could get what Windows 11 will look like), but what about the general polish of the OS? I mean, yes, it’s Windows after all and Microsoft wasn’t so good with designing any user interface in their entiry history of their existance, but let’s take a look. I must say, that the whole design looks dated after staring at it for about a week or so. Don’t get me wrong, there are even people trying to <a href="https://youtu.be/MzQblqLzSF4">switch out their Macs for that design</a>, but I am not really a fan of it anymore. I just don’t get it, this looks exactly like KDE Plasma 5 and they <a href="https://redd.it/oa53ii">even use the same wording in their ads</a>! Microsoft seems to not have it done right another time. Just no.</p><p></p><h2>Conclusions</h2><p></p><p>Windows 11 will still be the bloated mess that everyone knows and loves since decades. Nothing special has been added to Windows 11 what we Linux users already had in the 90s. This is a really disappointing OS and I hope Microsoft just gives up on Windows entirely. It’s on life support, embrace it!</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/windows-11.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/windows-11.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 17:31:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Getting the Corona Warn-App (and similar) to run on /e/OS]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Some of you already heard that I use /e/OS as a daily driver now. /e/OS is an operating system for mobile phones (a few of them to be precise) made by the /e/ foundation. Unlike traditional mobile operating systems like Android or iOS the whole thing doesn’t track you. I think your phone should be your phone and not Google’s or Apple’s. Recently after seeing the video by Laura and Aral I immediately noticed that other than iOS my other option towards a privacy-friendly, but low-cost mobile device would be /e/OS.</p><h2>So how do I install my COVID-19 tracking app?</h2><p>Here in Germany we have an app that’s called the Corona Warn-App, yours may be called differently, but the process is the same for every other app.</p><p>To get started you do these steps (assuming you got /e/OS installed):</p><p></p><ol><li>Unlock your phone</li><li>Swipe to the App store and tap the icon</li><li>Then you tap categories</li><li>If you are in the categories view you now scroll down and tap System apps</li><li>Afterwards you hit “Install” on the only app that’s there called “microG Exposure Notifications”</li><li>Then go back and hit the search icon and search for your desired COVID-19 tracking app made by your government and hit install there</li><li>Go to settings, system, microG and tap “Exposure Notifications” and enable it</li><li>Launch your COVID-19 tracking app and set it up.</li></ol><p>You are now helping you and others detecting COVID-19 in your area! 🎉</p><h2>References</h2><ul><li><a href="https://vimeo.com/342972799">The video by Laura Kalbag and Aral Balkan about “Small Tech”</a></li><li><a href="https://e.foundation/">/e/foundation website</a></li></ul>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/getting-the-corona-warn-app-and-similar-to-run-on-e-os.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/getting-the-corona-warn-app-and-similar-to-run-on-e-os.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 17:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The ly display manager]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago I found a nice TTY-based display manager. I know that some folks have put startx into their .bashrc or start it manually which is okay, but not nearly as good as having a full-blown display manager that starts fast and loads everything including your user session. ly is also included in koyuOS, my own operating system based on Arch Linux, because koyuOS should be as leightweight, but easy-to-use as possible. I think I found the middle-ground there. I think choosing ly was a better decision than lightdm, because display managers like these already load up a whole X server in itself which makes the bootup process a little slower. My current koyuOS installation is using EFISTUB so I don’t have to use bootloaders and all that crap to load up my OS, the EFI firmware on-board handles it all nicely for me. I also disabled NetworkManager-wait-online.service, because it heavily influenced boot times by a few seconds. I hope I could help and you should definitely use ly, it’s a great display manager.</p><p></p><h2>References</h2><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/koyuspace/koyuos">koyuOS</a></li><li><a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/ly/">ly on the AUR</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/nullgemm/ly">ly on GitHub</a></li></ul>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-ly-display-manager.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-ly-display-manager.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 18:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why I like the fediverse]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I have been a fediverse user pretty much almost since around when Google+ and Diaspora were a thing. What I liked about Diaspora specifically was that it was easy for me to reach people that have similar interests as me like anime, tech and music. My biggest interest in the fediverse was the open and diverse nature of the network, because unlike traditional social networks it gave me a reason to dig deeper into maintaining my own server which I did when I began hosting a Mastodon in April 2018. Also it was open-source and decentralized and gave me a lot of freedoms in terms of customizability.</p><p></p><p>If you know me a little longer you know how much I love customizing things (which might be the reason why I enjoy games like Minecraft or Sims so much, but that’ll be for another blog post). Also what about the people? A social network is worth nothing without users and that’s what is the driving motivation why I like the fediverse so much, because if I wanted to have my own social network I don’t have to start from scratch and can base on an existing network. As you can see the fediverse is a cool thing and I hope more and more websites use ActivityPub (especially Twitter) so others and me can follow people over there.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-i-like-the-fediverse.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/why-i-like-the-fediverse.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 18:28:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Exploring Gemini]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>After a bit passing of time I thought to have a look at the Gemini network and see what it has to offer. The best way to start getting into Gemini is going to the official website of Gemini and have a look at the clients and proxies. koyu.space also offers you a little bit of space for your own gemini capsule. A capsule is just a synonym for a website, but since Gemini isn’t the WWW it’s called a capsule.</p><p></p><h2>Differences between the WWW and Gemini</h2><p></p><p>Gemini URLs start with gemini:// and servers run on port 1965 (an unprivileged port). The file format for Gemini isn’t HTML, it’s GMI (short form of Gemini) with the unofficial MIME-type text/gemini. Files are served over a protocol using TCP and and modern features like TLS and GMI files are text-only with links to other capsules (just like in the early days of the WWW). Status codes are made up of two instead of three digets e.g. 2x means OK and 3x means redirect. User authentication can happen over input fields or cerificates (which is the recommended way), but so far no capsule utilizes user authentication. It has a search engine just like on the WWW, but is pretty barebones. Gemini also has mirrors of clearnet websites.</p><p></p><p>Taken from the project’s Gemini capsule it tries to be the following</p><p></p><ul><li>Is heavier than gopher</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Is lighter than the web</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Will not replace either</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Strives for maximum power to weight ratio</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Takes user privacy very seriously</li></ul><p></p><h2>Clients</h2><p></p><p>My clients of choice are AV-98 (CLI) and Lagrange (GUI). There are currently two proxies at portal.mozz.us (which I use) and at proxy.vulpes.one.</p><p></p><h2>Where to start and good sites</h2><p></p><p>If you want to host your own capsule you can set up your own VPS with a server software of your choice. You can also ask someone to host it for you, koyu.space and tilde.zone offer free space for your Gemini capsule.</p><p></p><p>Gemini directories inside of Gemini are available at medusae.space and directory.randomroad.net. geminispace.info is an updated version of the GUS search engine (which somehow doesn’t update its index since a few months as of writing). This blog is also available inside of Gemini.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/exploring-gemini.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/exploring-gemini.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 18:27:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The power of decentralization]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>So before Signal went down we were having some great discussions in our koyu.space Signal group. Now it’s been more than 24 hours since it’s down and this thanks to this guy.</p><p></p><p>[block]elon-signal[/block]</p><p></p><p>So why does decentralization matter? Well, it reduces the amount of friction if you want something that works reliably. For example if your server goes down one day, then you are the one you could point your fingers at. This makes such a network ultra-reliable if a user could just jump to the next available server. I think centralization of a network and therefore of power was never a great idea.</p><p></p><p>This is what I liked about the 90s web. Everyone was basically forced to have their own website and therefore compete with their raw information they shared. Blogs were ultra-popular until the early 2010s and I really liked it to read my favourite blogs, especially taking care of RSS Feed lists in my feedreader. This was way better than Facebook, Twitter and the sorts.</p><p></p><p>Then we also have the fediverse which is exchanging data all over the place. The cool thing about the fediverse is that information is getting spread across different servers (Mastodon for example caches text content from remote servers) and websites can intercommunicate with each other. This was the internet I was dreaming of when I was reading blogs most of the time. Being now a blog-owner myself would make me very proud if we had more people hosting a blog and sharing their ideas on the internet.</p><p></p><p>In the end nobody would really listen to me, but imagine what a wonderful world the internet could be if everyone had their own little space they own and control and host everything on their own.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-power-of-decentralization.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/the-power-of-decentralization.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rambling about Linux vs. Windows]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>After Effects alternative? Blender!<br/>GNOME for example uses it to create their 2D info graphic animations and AFAIK you can also add effects (which After Effects is all about)</p><p></p><p>Anti-cheat, I must say yes…that’s a thing, but that’s anti-competitive behaviour from Windows developers. Some developers even check and block Wine!</p><p></p><p>LibreOffice is a great office suite, it has everything I need and I even wrote my college papers on it. Works great!</p><p></p><p>CAD software is a whole different story and I hope there will be some good programs to do it right, same for very specialized Windows software for let’s say big machines.</p><p></p><p>These are just Windows/Linux side-by-side…but the end-goal of Linux is not growing bigger, it’s just to have a perfectly capable operating system for most people next to the proprietary walled gardens we already have for decades now. I think where Linux can shine is 1) everywhere else, but not on the desktop 2) the average grandma user that just wants to write them e-mails and surf “The Internet”.</p><p></p><p>Sure Linux has its advantages, but if we want to help it to grow we should get all the rather inexperienced people onto the boat and then laugh about hardcore Windows gamers then. But again: Linux’s end goal is not to grow bigger, it’s just an alternative (or better: a break) from all the garbled mess we have on the desktop.</p><p></p><p>What do I like about Windows?</p><p></p><ul><li>Great hardware compatibility</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Modern features well supported (disk encryption, TPM module configuration, OEM boot logo etc.)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Powerful applications (Adobe, MS Office etc.)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Games (sorry, Linux)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>A “known” thing everyone knows how to use it (because they probably already have a Windows computer at home)</li></ul><p></p><p>What am I not liking about Windows?</p><p></p><ul><li>Privacy</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Annoying nags (Cortana, Windows Update etc.)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Inconsistent user interface (Win32 VS UWP)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Almost empty Windows Store (Developers, Developers, Developers)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Stuff breaks more easily, especially after updates</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Messed up Spooler (printing is hell on Windows, really)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Gets slow over time forcing me to switch OS or hardware</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Preinstalled bloatware</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Stressful user interface</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Almost no freedoms changing things around to suit your needs</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Costs money even though they already serve ads and mine data</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Installer doesn’t like more than three drives and Windows Home only likes up to 16GB of RAM, Windows Pro only 2TB (but I would never be able to afford a machine with more than 2TB of RAM)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Community is almost dead, at least I barely get any help for my Windows system and have to fix stuff on blind luck alone</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Updates require a restart</li></ul><p></p><p>What do I like about Linux?</p><p></p><ul><li>A stable, fast and efficient system</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Hackable down to the core, literally</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Easy to use interface</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>No bloat, nags or crap</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Free (both cost and actual freedom)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Updates actually fix stuff</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Doesn’t slow down after more than half a year of use</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Simply is my friendliest companion</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Development is easy! (especially developing stuff for servers as they already run on Linux most of the time)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Installation just works (except if you use Ubuntu lol)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>If you don’t like it patch it out</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Generally smaller and less bloated (see above)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Hell lot of customization features (see above)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Somebody probably has a fix for it</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Huge and active community</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Updates don’t really require a restart and updates update everything on my system, both my software and my operating system</li></ul><p></p><p>What am I not liking about Linux? (and yes, it’s not perfect)</p><p></p><ul><li>It’s free if you don’t value your time</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Games (Windows just has too much of them)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Hardware support may be spotty (which is today almost not a problem and most of the time there are workarounds…thanks HP)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Not many vocal vendors selling Linux machines (which is the #1 reason why the Linux desktop isn’t there yet even though Linux was initially thought as a desktop OS)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Some OSS software isn’t as good as their proprietary counterparts (nothing can beat Adobe and it annoys the hell out of me that I can’t close Spotify to tray)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Fragmented choice of user interfaces and system base structures (makes it harder to optimize for one platform only, QT or GTK, does it have systemd etc.)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Butthurt /g/ community wanting to make Linux as inaccessible to “normies” as possible</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Some radical opinions about FLOSS and Stallman which I am not a fan of</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>Chicken-egg problem (with users come developers, but developers want users)</li></ul><p></p><p>TL;DR computers are garbage and society is shit. Linux rocks, but Windows does as well. I would prefer Linux though, because most of the time I spend on a computer is doing actual work and that’s where Linux can shine.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/rambling-about-linux-vs-windows.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/rambling-about-linux-vs-windows.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 18:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to plan and host a Mastodon instance]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>As you might have heard I host my own Mastodon instance with a few other people. You might plan to host your own as well (and in most cases create a single-user instance). Maybe you are not okay with the server you’re currently on or you want to get into the dirty bits of hosting and maintaining a Mastodon instance. In this guide you will find recommendations on how to host your own Mastodon instance and what issues you might encounter while running it.</p><p></p><h2>Resource consumption</h2><p></p><p>So before we start I’ll tell you what koyu.space consumes (a Mastodon instance with 2.1k users, an averaged-sized instance):</p><p></p><ul><li>12GB RAM in idle</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>40GB database storage (on a SSD, because we get a lot of queries)</li></ul><p></p><ul><li>More than 120GB of media (on a CDN, because it’s cheaper to host <em>that</em> many media files plus we don’t have the bandwidth to stream all this)</li></ul><p></p><p>So that might sound a lot, but that’s because we host user data of 2.1k people which are quite a lot. Your single-user instance might be happy with 2-4GB of RAM and 20GB for the DB and OS plus a CDN (because maybe you have way too many cat pictures to post).</p><p></p><h2>Hosting providers</h2><p></p><h3>masto.host</h3><p></p><p>masto.host is a very friendly and easy way to start your new Mastodon instance. Just sign up and it works. Hugo is a nice guy and fixed a lot of issues I encountered when I was having my instance over there. The only downside is that you don’t get into the fun stuff on actually hosting and maintaining a Mastodon instance, but it’s a good thing if you have no idea what you’re doing and you’re still not ready to play with the big guns (a Linux console). You can get a Mastodon instance up and running in 24 hours and servers start at six bucks a month. You can choose a subdomain (which is free) or bring in your own (they usually start at 90 cents per year, especially .xyz domains). If you plan to modify Mastodon and want to run it then you can’t do it here for security reasons.</p><p></p><h3>DigitalOcean</h3><p></p><p>DigitalOcean is the next host I can recommend for people who want to tinker with a Linux system and want to set up everything by themselves. They also have been successful if I had any issues. The only problem is that it might get expensive over time. Otherwise their servers run stable and fast as well which is pretty much needed for Mastodon (especially disk bandwidth for the database).</p><p></p><h2>Setup and Help</h2><p></p><p>If you use Masto.host your Mastodon instance is already set up. It’s fully-managed hosting after all meaning you get a Mastodon instance without lifting a finger. On DigitalOcean on the other hand you have two options where one has been proven the most successful. First the DigitalOcean Markteplace already has an image with Mastodon preinstalled, but most of the time it’s a very outdated version and I am not even sure if it works correctly once set up. The other option (which is also the best) is to install it manually. You can follow the instructions over on <a href="https://docs.joinmastodon.org/">docs.joinmastodon.org</a> which are very detailed and explain the topic very well. If you plan to have users and want them to receive e-mails you also have to get an SMTP server from somwhere. I was pretty happy with <a href="http://mailbox.org/">mailbox.org</a> which want 2,50€ a month so they can continue to offer their services while being privacy-friendly (and their mail service is very fitting for a support desk+Mastodon mailer). Also a good thing about their service is that I was able to pay with my debit card over PayPal, because I don’t own a credit card, but they also offer more payment options one of which is the anonymous Paysafecard (which you can get in every gas station here in Germany and pay with cash which is the most anonymous way to pay).</p><p></p><p>So these are my recommendations on how to get started on hosting your own Mastodon instance. I hope I could open up your eyes a little bit and if you need a little help you can reach me on IRC at irc.koyu.space or via e-mail on me@koyu.space. Thanks for reading!</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/how-to-plan-and-host-a-mastodon-instance.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/how-to-plan-and-host-a-mastodon-instance.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 18:22:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to compile butt on Solus]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>This is a small tutorial on how I got <code>butt</code> (broadcast using this tool) working on Solus.</p><p></p><p>First download the source code from here: <a href="https://danielnoethen.de/butt/">https://danielnoethen.de/butt/</a></p><p></p><p>and extract it. Now navigate to that folder with your terminal and issue the following commands in that folder.</p><p></p><p>Install compiler and dependencies:</p><p></p><p>sudo eopkg install -c system.devel<br/><br/>  <br/><br/>sudo eopkg install libogg-devel libvorbis-devel lame-devel libflac-devel portaudio-devel libsamplerate-devel fdk-aac-devel fltk-devel opus-devel libx11-devel bdwgc-dbginfo libpng-devel fontconfig-devel libxfixes-devel libxext-devel libxft-devel</p><p></p><p>Compile butt:</p><p></p><p>./configure --prefix=/usr<br/><br/>make -j4<br/><br/>sudo make install</p><p></p><p>Now run the command butt from your terminal 🎉</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/how-to-compile-butt-on-solus.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/how-to-compile-butt-on-solus.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 17:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A quick introduction to the Fediverse]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><em>Updated: May 5 2022</em></p><p></p><p>The Fediverse is a word consisting of “federation” and “universe” and is a place on the internet where a lot of people are communicating. It’s a social media platform, but can be more than this. It’s weird and exciting and I love that.</p><p></p><p>While you heard of Twitter and Facebook, you probably haven’t heard about Mastodon, Akkoma, GNU Social and PeerTube, right? These other things are social media platforms like the big brothers, but with a twist. Instead of relying on one big server, everything is being spread out. The data, moderation, costs and so on are all in the hands of it’s users.</p><p></p><p>The Fediverse kinda works like E-Mail. You don’t have to be on one server to communicate with people from another server and if one server goes down the rest of the network keeps running. This also means you can have a couple of different accounts on other servers with the same e-mail address as well (these are called “alts”).</p><p></p><p>So if I am on koyu.space and you are on e.g. mastodon.social then I could just go and interact with you like we were on the same site. It doesn’t have to be Mastodon you’re going with.</p><p></p><p>Imagine you could comment a video on YouTube with your Facebook account without having to register for YouTube. This already works for the fediverse: If you’re posting a comment with Akkoma on a PeerTube video it magically appears on the PeerTube video.</p><p></p><p>Every software implementing the protocols used for federation (usually ActivityPub) can be in the fediverse! Most of this software also has features that set it apart from the usual big social networks.</p><p></p><p>While the userbase of the fediverse is relatively small it’s a good alternative to currently well-established social networks. You will find people there in all shapes and sizes and maybe you will find people you can sympathize with.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://leonie.lgbt/blog/a-quick-introduction-to-the-fediverse.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://leonie.lgbt/blog/a-quick-introduction-to-the-fediverse.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
