<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[koyu's personal website]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[koyu's personal website]]></description>
        <link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 17:39:39 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="null/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[freiOS: A New Way to Experience Computing]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been hunting for a fresh, secure, and lightweight operating system, then freiOS might just be the breath of fresh air you need. Built with simplicity, speed, and security in mind, freiOS isn’t just another OS — it’s a platform designed for users who value efficiency, sustainability, and privacy.</p><h3>A Modern Approach to OS Design</h3><p>What really sets freiOS apart is its focus on performance without compromising security. When you boot it up, you’re not only greeted with a sleek interface but also a fast, responsive environment that works seamlessly on both modern and older hardware. You won’t find bloated features slowing you down here; instead, it’s all about doing more with less. Whether you’re managing daily tasks, running productivity apps, or just browsing the web, freiOS ensures your computer stays fast and secure, even under load.</p><h3>Built-In Security</h3><p>In today’s digital world, data privacy is more important than ever, and freiOS takes that seriously. The OS incorporates strong encryption protocols and built-in privacy features to ensure your data stays safe, no matter what you’re doing. freiOS is a trustworthy option for users who want to maintain control over their personal information. Whether you’re using it for personal tasks or business work, you can rely on its built-in features to keep your data secure.</p><h3>Efficiency Meets Simplicity</h3><p>One of the standout features of freiOS is its intuitive, minimalist GNOME desktop environment. There’s no overwhelming clutter, just a straightforward workspace where everything is where it needs to be. This user-centric design is perfect for those who value a clean, distraction-free computing experience. Whether you’re working from home or on the go, freiOS provides the right tools to get the job done quickly and efficiently.</p><p>And with full localization options, it’s easy to adapt to your own preferences and language. The system supports a wide range of regional settings, such as date formats and currency symbols, ensuring a smooth experience regardless of your location.</p><h3>Out-of-the-Box Essentials</h3><p>FreiOS doesn’t leave you hanging when it comes to apps. It comes preloaded with the essential tools you need to get started. LibreOffice, for word processing and spreadsheets, Evolution for managing email and calendar, and more. You won’t have to scramble around downloading software just to get productive. Plus, the OS integrates seamlessly with services that most users rely on for their daily tasks, making it a great choice right from the start.</p><h3>Hardware Compatibility and Longevity</h3><p>Not only does it offer performance, but freiOS is also designed to be hardware-friendly. Whether you’re using an old laptop or a modern desktop, it supports a wide range of components, including graphics cards from Nvidia, AMD, and Intel. The system also provides pre-configured ISO files that make installation a breeze — no headache, just an easy setup that works from the get-go.</p><p>By optimizing the OS for both modern and older hardware, freiOS is contributing to the reduction of electronic waste — a huge benefit in today’s environmentally conscious world. Its lightweight design allows older systems to run smoothly, helping them stay relevant longer and saving them from obsolescence.</p><h3>A Perfect Fit for Local Needs</h3><p>What makes freiOS even more compelling is how it’s subtly optimized for local needs. While it’s designed to be a globally accessible operating system, freiOS takes into account the specifics of the German market. It integrates regional settings like language, date formats, and even currency symbols to provide a more seamless and familiar experience for German users. These thoughtful details ensure that the system feels intuitive and efficient for those based in Germany, further enhancing its usability and appeal.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>If you’re looking for an operating system that values speed, security, and sustainability, freiOS should definitely be on your radar. With its user-friendly interface, solid security, seamless hardware compatibility, and thoughtful design, it’s a great choice for anyone from casual users to those who want to push the boundaries of their machines. The future of computing is clean, efficient, and secure, and freiOS is paving the way.</p><p>Whether you’re tired of bloated, slow systems or just want something more minimalist and dependable, freiOS gives you everything you need to get the job done. Give it a try and experience computing in a whole new way.</p><p>[card]freios-post[/card]</p>]]></description>
            <link>null/posts/freios-a-new-way-to-experience-computing</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">null/posts/freios-a-new-way-to-experience-computing</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 08:18:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[koyu.space was still here all the time – now as a PDS!]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>koyu.space has been quietly present for a while, but it’s been a little less vocal about its existence lately. That’s changing now. koyu.space has evolved into a Personal Data Server (PDS), making it part of the decentralized social web.</p><h2>What does that mean?</h2><p>koyu.space now operates on the <a href="https://atproto.com/">Authenticated Transfer Protocol (AT Protocol)</a>, the same protocol that powers <a href="https://bsky.app/">Bluesky</a>. Unlike traditional social media platforms, where all your data is locked into a single company’s walled garden, a PDS lets you have more control over your information. You’re not just the product – you’re the one holding the keys to your own data.</p><p>If you were part of koyu.space before, or you’re curious about what’s different now, I’m opening up invites for the next chapter of this journey! If you’d like to join, just reach out to me, and I’ll send you an invite.</p><h2>Bluesky vs. Mastodon</h2><p>While we’re on the topic of decentralized platforms, let’s talk a bit about how Bluesky compares to Mastodon – two popular alternatives to traditional social media.</p><p>Both are part of the Fediverse, but Bluesky runs on the AT Protocol, while Mastodon uses ActivityPub. The AT Protocol offers some key advantages:</p><ol><li><strong>Improved Scalability and Performance</strong>: Bluesky’s protocol is designed with scalability in mind. It handles large volumes of traffic and user data with greater efficiency, making it a smoother experience for users. Mastodon, on the other hand, can sometimes struggle with performance due to its decentralized nature, especially on smaller instances.</li><li><strong>Better Data Control</strong>: The AT Protocol gives users more control over their data. It allows for features like private profiles, content moderation at the individual level, and greater customization. Mastodon does offer some of these features, but Bluesky’s implementation is more streamlined and accessible.</li><li><strong>Ease of Use</strong>: Bluesky’s user interface is sleek and designed with simplicity in mind. It’s easy to navigate, and you don’t have to worry about joining a specific instance or server to participate. Mastodon can be more complicated for newcomers because it requires joining specific instances that have different rules, policies, and content moderation standards.</li><li><strong>Cross-Platform Compatibility</strong>: Bluesky, due to its protocol design, is built to be more compatible with other platforms and social networks in the future. It provides a strong foundation for expanding the decentralized web. Mastodon has made incredible progress, but its ecosystem still feels somewhat segmented.</li><li><strong>Storage Efficiency</strong>: One of the standout advantages of Bluesky is that it doesn’t fill up your storage the way Mastodon can. Mastodon’s backend is notoriously inefficient, and my previous instance on Mastodon collected over <strong>3TB</strong> of data before it was shut down. This massive amount of data just from running an instance made it increasingly difficult to maintain and scale. Bluesky’s more efficient infrastructure ensures that data doesn’t accumulate unnecessarily, making it far easier to manage.</li></ol><p>That said, both Bluesky and Mastodon are excellent options for those looking to move away from centralized social media. It all comes down to what you value more: performance and scalability, or community-driven moderation and openness.</p><p>If you’re ready to explore a more decentralized way of socializing, join koyu.space and start engaging with a new kind of platform.</p><p>See you there! 🚀</p><p>[block]bluesky-embed-1[/block]</p>]]></description>
            <link>null/posts/koyu-space-was-still-here-all-the-time-now-as-a-pds</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">null/posts/koyu-space-was-still-here-all-the-time-now-as-a-pds</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Back in the Ink: A Fresh Start with Splatoon 3]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>For a while, my Switch Lite sat forgotten, gathering dust in the corner. I had moved on to other things, including The Finals, my competitive shooter of choice on Linux. But a recent disaster—when The Finals completely broke after a frustrating update—finally pushed me to dust off my old console. The game wouldn’t even launch anymore, and after countless tweaks to make it work on Linux, I was done. I needed something fresh, and that’s when I found Splatoon 3.</p><p></p><p>I’ve never been part of the Splatoon craze. I missed the hype around the first two games, never owned a Wii U, and didn’t get into the series until the third installment. But once I fired up Splatoon 3, I was hooked immediately. This game is something else.</p><p></p><p>The vibe of Splatoon 3? Electric. The city is vibrant and full of life, and the music is a hyperactive blend of squid-pop that matches the action on screen. But beyond the charming aesthetic, the core gameplay is what keeps me coming back. It’s a turf war where your weapon of choice is ink, and the goal is to cover as much ground as possible while splatting opponents. It’s addicting. The strategy involved in choosing your weapons, balancing your loadout, and coordinating with teammates makes it feel less like a simple shooter and more like a competitive dance with ink and paint.</p><p></p><p>And now, with the official announcement of the Switch 2, I’m even more excited. Sure, there have been rumors and leaks for months, but the real deal is finally here. As we inch closer to its release, I can’t help but imagine how Splatoon 3’s ink-splattering chaos will look on a beefier console with better graphics and smoother framerates. But despite the hype for the new hardware, there’s something oddly satisfying about revisiting a system that’s past its prime. It’s like rereading a favorite book before you dive into a new series—familiar but still thrilling.</p><p></p><p>For now, though, I’m content to stay in the world of Splatoon 3. It’s the right game at the right time. I’m having a blast dodging rollers, launching Tenta Missiles, and trying to keep up with the player who’s always just a little bit too good. The ink might dry eventually, but right now, I’m just soaking in every colorful, chaotic moment.</p><p></p><p>As for The Finals, I’ll be back once the game recovers from its latest break. Version 5.6 has completely broken the game on Linux, and until that gets patched, I’m staying in Splatoon 3’s world of ink-splattered mayhem. Here’s to new memories, one splash at a time.</p>]]></description>
            <link>null/posts/back-in-the-ink-a-fresh-start-with-splatoon-3</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">null/posts/back-in-the-ink-a-fresh-start-with-splatoon-3</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 08:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>